<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mystery of iniquity unfolded, or, The false apostles and the authors of popery compared in their secular design and means of accomplishing it by corrupting the Christian religion under pretence of promoting it</title>
            <author>Allen, William, d. 1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 171 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 82 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A23667</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A1066</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10549</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12714068</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12714068</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66155</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A23667)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66155)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 372:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mystery of iniquity unfolded, or, The false apostles and the authors of popery compared in their secular design and means of accomplishing it by corrupting the Christian religion under pretence of promoting it</title>
                  <author>Allen, William, d. 1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22], 141 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.M. for Walter Kettilby ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to William Allen. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Corinne Vieracker</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66155:1"/>
            <p>THE MYSTERY OF INIQUITY UNFOLDED: OR, The Falſe Apoſtles and the Authors of <hi>POPERY</hi> compared, in their ſecular Deſign and Means of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhing it, by Corrupting the Chriſtian Religion, under pretence of Promoting it.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>John 7.18.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>He that ſpeaketh of himſelf, ſeeketh his own glory.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 Tim. 6.5.</hi>
               </bibl> 
               <p>Men of corrupt minds, and deſtrtute of the truth, ſuppoſing that gain is Godlineſs.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. M.</hi> for <hi>Walter Kettilby,</hi> at the <hi>Biſhop</hi>'s <hi>Head</hi> in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Church-Yard.</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:66155:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66155:2"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE deſign of the following <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe</hi> is to ſhew that <hi>Popery</hi> is founded in a like <hi>worldly corrupt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> as the <hi>way of the falſe Apoſtles</hi> was, <hi>and carried on by a like Art.</hi> And if it ſhall appear to be ſo indeed, there will be no great cauſe to marvel, why the many worthy endeavours of the <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Cauſe</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the <hi>Papiſts</hi> of being guilty of <hi>cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting</hi> the Chriſtian Religion, ſhould prevail no more upon them than they have done; for ſuch an <hi>Intereſt</hi> whileſt adhered to, doth obſtruct the operation of all ſuch Truth on the Mind and Will, as tends to oppoſe or undermine it. So that upon the former ſuppoſition, we may well conceive, that the reaſon why
<pb facs="tcp:66155:3"/>the endeavours of the Perſons aforeſaid have prevailed no more upon the Gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers, is not the weakneſs of their Cauſe, nor weakneſs in their managing of it, nor yet the ſtrength of their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries Arguments in oppoſing them: but the true reaſon will be found to lye in the prevalence of a <hi>carnal, worldly corrupt Intereſt.</hi> For that which was the reaſon why the Holy Apoſtles could not recover the <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> nor thoſe that ſtuck to them, from their <hi>Errors</hi> and <hi>Corruptions,</hi> we may well conceive to be the reaſon likewiſe, why the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates for Reformation have recovered no more than they have done of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> neither from <hi>theirs,</hi> which were introduced into the world, and perſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in upon the ſame or like carnal rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and motive, as the Corruptions of the falſe Apoſtles were.</p>
            <p>Now our Adverſaries themſelves can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but grant that the reaſon why the Holy Apoſtles prevailed no more upon the falſe Apoſtles and their followers than they did, in managing the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Cauſe againſt them in corrupting the
<pb facs="tcp:66155:3"/>Chriſtian Religion, was neither the bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their <hi>own,</hi> nor goodneſs of their <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries Cauſe,</hi> nor the Holy Apoſtles weak managing of their <hi>Cauſe:</hi> and if none of theſe were the reaſon, what elſe could it be in probability, but the falſe Apoſtles love of, cloſe adherence to, and faſt holding of ſuch a <hi>corrupt Intereſt,</hi> as could not be <hi>upheld</hi> but by <hi>corrupting</hi> the Chriſtian Religion? And if the Holy Apoſtles who were extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily aſſiſted in delivering and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Truth, and who had their Doctrine extraordinarily confirmed with Signs, and Wonders, and divers Miracles, could not for all that prevail with the falſe Apoſtles to confeſs and relinquiſh their Errors, ſo long as a Worldly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt was upheld by thoſe Errors, and was dearer to them than the Truth it ſelf; 'tis then no wonder at all if our Proteſtant Advocates, who do not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to compare with the Apoſtles, have prevailed no more neither than they have done, (though their Cauſe be never ſo good, and ſo well managed,) to bring Popiſh Guides to acknowledge and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquiſh
<pb facs="tcp:66155:4"/>thoſe Errors of theirs, by which their corrupt Intereſt is ſupported and maintained, if that Intereſt is dearer to them alſo than that Truth that oppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it, and fights againſt it, is, as there is too much ground to ſuſpect it is.</p>
            <p>Some perhaps may be under a tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptation, to have the more favourable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion of Popery, for that there have been men of great Parts and Learning of that way; who upon that account may perhaps be thought as able as their Adverſaries to diſcern Truth from Error. But if thoſe, who ſo think, will but conſider, that thoſe Learned men have ſtill had a ſtrong byas of a corrupt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt to draw them aſide; they may eaſily relieve themſelves againſt ſuch a temptation. For the greater parts ſuch men have, as have eſpouſed a corrupt Intereſt, and are ſtrongly bent to defend it, the leſs likely are they to be over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come meerly by Truth: Becauſe it hath always been too common with ſuch men to imploy all their Parts and Learning to the uttermoſt, not indifferently and impartially to ſeek Truth for Truths ſake,
<pb facs="tcp:66155:4"/>but to make the beſt they can of the Cauſe they have undertaken, and with all poſſible Art to dreſs it up, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they, nor any of their party may fall into diſlike of it. Which was the reaſon why the learned Scribes, Lawyers, Phariſees, and Rulers among the Jews, ſtood it out againſt Chriſt, when the more illiterate and meaner ſort that were not under ſuch a temptation of a worldly intereſt as the others were, nor had ſuch parts to ſtrengthen them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their oppoſition as the others had, were ſooner brought to receive Chriſt and ſubmit to his Doctrine. Of ſuch as the former ſort our Saviour ſaid, <hi>how can ye believe which ſeek ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour one of another, and ſeek not the honour which comes from God only?</hi> Joh. <hi>5.44.</hi> The experience of ſuch a thing as this, doubtleſs occaſioned that ſaying of St. <hi>Paul, 1 Cor. 1.26. You ſee your calling brethren, how that not many wiſe men after the fleſh are called, nor many mighty, nor many noble.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66155:5"/>
            <p>Beſides, as the Love of a corrupt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in men calls off their thoughts from an impartial enquiry after Truth, eſpecially ſuch Truth as oppoſeth it; ſo it corrupts the mind and clouds the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of Learned as well as <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, in making a Judgment of what's Truth and what's Error, in thoſe things wherein ſuch an Intereſt is concerned. 'Tis ſaid a <hi>Gift blindeth the wiſe and perverteth the judgment of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous,</hi> Exod. <hi>23.8.</hi> It hinders a man from enquiring impartially into the right of the others cauſe againſt whom he hath received a bribe: and cauſeth him with as much partiality to conſider his, from whom he hath received it, and is a byas as well as a cloud upon his mind in forming a judgment upon the Cauſe before him: by reaſon of all which he gives judgment againſt the truth and equity of the Cauſe. And there is the ſame reaſon why a corrupt Intereſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, ſhould hinder a right judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and determination in matters wherein that Intereſt is ſtruck at, as
<pb facs="tcp:66155:5"/>there is, why the corrupt Intereſt of a bribe ſhould hinder it, in a man other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe knowing and wiſe.</p>
            <p>Our Saviour ſaith, <hi>if thine eye be evil, thy whole body ſhall be full of darkneſs: if therefore the light that is in thee be darkneſs, how great is that darkneſs?</hi> Mat. <hi>6.23.</hi> If the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning principle in man be corrupt, as it is when that which is predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is covetouſneſs or the love of the world, (of which he there ſpeaks) the iſſues of it can be no more pure than the ſtreams that flow from a corrupt Fountain: that corrupt governing prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple will ſtill be turning men aſide in particular actions of their Lives, and in making a judgment of thoſe things wherein their corrupt Intereſt is oppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or immediately or remotely ſtruck at. <hi>For men cannot ſerve God and Mammon</hi> (as there it follows) they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be faithful to God and his Truth, where a love to him and a care to pleaſe him, do not bear a greater ſway than love to <hi>Mammon</hi> or any other worldly concern doth.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66155:6"/>
            <p>Add we yet to all this one conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration more, and that is, That when men have more love for, and pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, for worldly advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage ſake, than love to Truth for Truths ſake, and what attends a ſincere receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it, the Scripture hath told us, <hi>that for that very cauſe God ſhall ſend ſuch</hi> (learned men not excepted) <hi>ſtrong deluſions, that they ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve a lie;</hi> to think and believe veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they have faſt hold of Truth, when yet <hi>they have but a lie in their right hand, 2</hi> Theſ. <hi>2.10, 11, 12.</hi> God in juſt judgment giving them up to an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judicious mind to call evil good, and good evil.</p>
            <p>Theſe things ſhew how little in reaſon the conſideration of the learning and parts of any of the Popiſh party ought to weigh with thoſe who upon the account of them are inclined to entertain any whit the more favourable opinion of their way, when they conſider as they ought, that their Learning and Parts are in conjunction with a corrupt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66155:6"/>
            <p>As for the Laity or Common people of the Popiſh perſwaſion, I will not ſay, that a worldly corrupt Intereſt doth ſo much prevail on them <hi>immediately,</hi> to be or to continue to be what they are in point of Popery, as it doth with their Clergie; but at the <hi>Second hand</hi> it doth prevail on them alſo. For they acting by an Implicite faith, believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as their Church-men believe, and ſeeing not with their own, but with <hi>their</hi> eyes, and taking all on truſt from them, and giving up themſelves intirely to their Conduct; it follows neceſſarily, that if a corrupt Intereſt miſguide their Guides, <hi>they</hi> alſo muſt needs become ſeduced by means of it. So that what was ſaid to the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> of old, is truly applicable unto them: <hi>O my people, they which lead thee cauſe thee to err.</hi> But that will be no excuſe to them who ſuffer themſelves to be ſo miſled: <hi>For if the blind lead the blind,</hi> you know who hath ſaid, <hi>they both ſhall fall into the ditch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if Popery ſhall be found indeed
<pb facs="tcp:66155:7"/>to be founded in a like ſecular carnal corrupt Intereſt as the corrupt Doctrine and Practice of the falſe Apoſtles was, (and whether it be or no, I leave you to judge by what the following diſcourſe offers you) then that alone would be enough to blaſt the Reputation of it for ever in the minds of all ſuch as have judgment in Spiritual things. For by this very thing did St. <hi>John</hi> diſcriminate the falſe Teachers and Degenerate Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and their way, from the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox and Sincere, and <hi>their</hi> way.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>They,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are of the world, therefore ſpeak they of the world, and the world heareth them. 1</hi> Jo. <hi>4.5, 6. They are of the world, i. e.</hi> they were men of worldly minds, and ſuch as chiefly deſigned a worldly Intereſt, they were ſuch as did <hi>mind earthly things,</hi> as it is elſewhere expreſt, <hi>Phil. 3.18.</hi> therefore they <hi>ſpeak of the world, i. e.</hi> the Doctrine which they taught, ſo far as it was Falſe, was calculated to promote a worldly corrupt Intereſt: <hi>And the world heareth them,</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:66155:7"/>is, earthly minded men, pretenders to Religion, received their Doctrine as falling in with their worldly deſign. But <hi>we,</hi> ſaith St. John, <hi>are of God, he that knoweth God, heareth us, i. e.</hi> received their Doctrine which drew men off from the world to God: <hi>He that is not of God, heareth not us: Hereby know we the Spirit of Truth, and the Spirit of error:</hi> behold here a plain Diſcrimination of who, and whoſe way is of God, and whoſe is not, with whom the Spirit of Truth is found, and with whom the Spirit of Error.</p>
            <p>If the Authors of Popery then, and their followers, have adopted into their Religion as a part of it, any corrupt Doctrine or Practice for worldly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage ſake, as the falſe Teachers of old did; then <hi>they,</hi> we ſee, as well as thoſe falſe Teachers, are markt out by St. <hi>John,</hi> as being not of God, but of the world, and as men that are miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided by a Spirit of Errour. And although by wreſting the Scriptures and corrupting the Word of God, they think
<pb facs="tcp:66155:8"/>to colour over and patronize their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Doctrines and Practices, juſt as the falſe Apoſtles before them did; yet their Arguings thence, are but of the ſame nature with the Reaſonings of the falſe Apoſtles in like caſes, which were, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls them, but <hi>perverſe diſputings of men of corrupt minds, deſtitute of the truth, ſuppoſing that gain is godlineſs, 1</hi> Tim. <hi>6.5.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have in the following Papers ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed how St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Complying with the Jews in ſome Rites of the Jewiſh wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, upon account of Expedience, was quite of a different nature from the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Complyances of the falſe Apoſtles and their party And from that pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential and expediential complyance of his, I have in an Appendix by parity of Reaſon argued the expediency of yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the uſe of ſome things in or about the external form of Gods Worſhip, which are neither directly commanded nor forbidden by God, when circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances render ſuch a yielding neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to prevent Diviſions in the Church,
<pb facs="tcp:66155:8"/>and the bad Conſequences of them, and to preſerve Peace and Charity in it, and the better to further the free courſe of the Goſpel. And this I have done the rather, leſt any ſhould think that ſuch a yielding as aforeſaid, ſhould be of like nature with thoſe corrupt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances of the falſe Apoſtles and their Party, which are repreſented to view in the following Diſcourſe.</p>
            <p>As for thoſe who have hitherto eſcap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſnares of Popery, the proper uſe of the enſuing Tract for them, is, to fortifie them againſt all Temptations of turning Papiſts, of what nature ſoever the Temptation may be: Always re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring, that ſuch as follow the falſe Apoſtles in corrupting the Chriſtian Religion to avoid Perſecution, or for any worldly advantage whatſoever, muſt expect to ſhare with them in their <hi>fate</hi> alſo, of whom it is ſaid, <hi>their end ſhall be according to their works, 2</hi> Cor. <hi>11.15.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſince you will find by the proceſs of the Diſcourſe before you, that the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions both in Faith and Practice,
<pb facs="tcp:66155:9"/>firſt in the falſe Apoſtles and their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, and after them in the Papiſts, did ariſe and ſpring out of an <hi>inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate</hi> love of the world: the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof may ſerve as a Sea-mark to warn us to take heed of that Rock up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which ſo many profeſſours of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity have made ſhipwrack of it. This running into the Spirit of the World, hath always been fatal to the Churches: As it laid waſte at laſt the once famous flouriſhing Churches of the Apoſtles own planting; ſo it hath ſince depreſt and kept many others very low in their Spiritual ſtate, and is of ill abode, as to their future ſtanding. And there is ſo much the more danger of falling into an undue and deſtructive love of the things of this world, becauſe we have need of them, daily uſe them, familiarly converſe with them: and becauſe men ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally are very unable to diſcern the parting difference between a lawful and unlawful degree of love to them, and ſo are very apt inſenſibly to paſs over from the one into the other. And therefore
<pb facs="tcp:66155:9"/>there is great reaſon to be jealous of our affections in this reſpect, and diligent to obſerve their motion and manner of operation towards the world, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to be following them with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations, that all the things of this world are at beſt but Temporal, and uſeful only for a little ſeaſon, and that our main Concern lies in the things of another world that are for Eternity; in compariſon of which, the things of this World are of no weight, when a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and estimate of both is rightly made. By the Knowledge, Belief, and practical conſideration of this it was, that the Holy Apoſtles and all ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtans then, did overcome the world, when their worldly and ſpiritual, their temporal and eternal Intereſt came in competition. <hi>This is the victory that overcometh the world, even our faith,</hi> ſaith St. John, <hi>1</hi> Ep. <hi>5.4. And though our outward man periſh, yet the inward man is renewed day by day, while we look not at the things which are ſeen, but the things which
<pb facs="tcp:66155:10"/>are not ſeen; for the things which are ſeen, are temporal, but the things which are not ſeen, are eternal,</hi> ſaith St. Paul, <hi>2</hi> Cor. <hi>4.16, 18.</hi> And it was by that <hi>ſaith</hi> which is the <hi>Subſtance or confident expectation of things hoped for, and the evidence of things not ſeen,</hi> by which <hi>Abraham, Moſes</hi> and the reſt of thoſe Worthies in elder times, became ſuch famous inſtances of overcoming the world, as they were, <hi>Heb. 11.</hi> And our bleſſed Saviour <hi>for the Joy that was ſet before him, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured the Croſs and deſpiſed the ſhame,</hi> yea and contemned the Grandeur of the world too, when he was tempted thereby to that which was incongruous to the end of his coming.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall think the publiſhing of theſe papers might well be ſpared, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the many tranſcending pieces againſt Popery which are already ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant; I confeſs I ſhould have thought ſo too, (eſpecially conſidering the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor) had it not been that the way of proceeding againſt Popery uſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in,
<pb facs="tcp:66155:10"/>by comparing it with the corrupt Religion of the falſe Apoſtles, hath not, ſo far as I have obſerved, been much made uſe of by others, unleſs only in ſome glances which look that way. And yet what can expoſe Popery more to the diſlike, even of every vulgar apprehenſion, than to diſcover its like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to the Religion of the falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, who preached Chriſt indeed as theſe of this way alſo do, but they did it not ſincerely, but added to, and mixt with the doctrine and Religion of Chriſt, and that as neceſſary to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, things of quite a different nature and contrary tendency, even as theſe likewiſe do, <hi>Phil. 1.15, 16.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, as by diſcovering the true nature of the corrupt Religion of the falſe Apoſtles and their Proſelytes, (a thing which is endeavoured in the following diſcourſe) we may take meaſure of, and eſtimate the nature of Popery when we find, as we may, a likeneſs between them; So per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps the Readers of more <hi>ordinary</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:66155:11"/>Capacities, may find ſuch further bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit thereby, as to come to a better un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of many places and paſſages in the Holy Apoſtles Epiſtles, relating to the way of falſe Teachers, as, without knowing in ſome meaſure what the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt Principles and Practices of the falſe Apoſtles were and their ill effects in the Churches, can hardly be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. And if that may, though nothing elſe ſhould, be gained thereby, yet that alone I hope would in ſome meaſure recompence the pains of <hi>ſuch</hi> Readers in peruſing the ſaid diſcourſe: From which I ſhall detain them no longer, this being all I have to ſay by way of preface; craving their pardon for the length of it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:66155:11"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:66155:12"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66155:12"/>
            <head>THE MYSTERY OF INIQUITY UNFOLDED.</head>
            <p>BY a collection of ſundry paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages ſcattered up and down in the Writings of the Holy Apoſtles of our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, it may eaſily be diſcerned how and for what end, and under what pretence the falſe Apoſtles in the Primitive times corrupted the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And by comparing here-with the Chriſtian Religion as now corrupted by Popery, together with its end and deſign, and the <hi>pretence</hi> under which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66155:13"/>it hath been managed by the Authors of it, and Guides of the people of that perſwaſion, thoſe that halt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two opinions in the Caſe to be enquired into, and that have any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be led into the way of Truth on which hand ſoever it falls, may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily come to a clear Reſolution and full ſatisfaction, who are in the error, the Papiſts or the Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>In order to the Compariſon thus to be made, and to the ſatisfaction that is thereby to be attained, I muſt repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to you from the Scriptures theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. What the deſign of the falſe Apoſtles was in managing the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an profeſſion to ſo ill purpoſe as they did.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In what way and by what means, they carried on their deſign. After I have done this I ſhall draw the Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel between the falſe Apoſtles and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of Popery, and ſhew how the Authors of Popery have followed the falſe Apoſtles in both End and Means.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66155:13"/>
            <p>S. 1. I ſhall begin with the firſt of theſe, and ſhew what the deſign of the falſe Apoſtles was in managing the Chriſtian profeſſion ſo unchriſtianly as they did. And to make way for the better underſtanding of that, I ſhall briefly touch upon the <hi>Riſe</hi> of them, and the occaſion of it. The ſincere profeſſion of Chriſtianity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing attended at the firſt, and for a long time after, with ſore perſecution; there were ſome of that Profeſſion, and probably Teachers too, who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither willing wholly to relin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh it, nor yet to ſuffer ſo much as a faithful and thorough adherence to the doctrine and precepts of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel did expoſe men to; did caſt about how they might retain a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Goſpel, and yet avoid any great or conſiderable ſuffering for it: And in concluſion reſolved upon this, <hi>viz.</hi> to <hi>Comply</hi> with their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries in ſome things pertaining to the Religion and way which they profeſt, (of which I ſhall ſpeak more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly afterwards) whereby they took
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:66155:14"/>off the keenneſs of their oppoſition, and provided for their own eaſe and ſecurity. Some pretences they found out for ſo doing, wherewith they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ſatisfie themſelves, and others (as well as they could) whom they laboured to draw in to make a party: Juſt as St. <hi>Paul</hi> foretold the Elders of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Of your own ſelves ſhall men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away Diſciples after them,</hi> Acts 20.30.</p>
            <p>And being oppoſed herein by the faithful Apoſtles, they uſed all the art they could to defend and juſtifie what they had done, and had perſwaded others to do. And to render the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition they had herein from the holy Apoſtles the leſs available in the eyes of others, they ſought by one means or another to diſparage them, and to undermine the authority and reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they had in the hearts of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians. And by theſe means they cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted and drew away many after them; and that not of the more ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Diſciples only, but probably ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66155:14"/>of thoſe alſo who were become preachers of the Goſpel; whereof it may be <hi>Demas</hi> might be one, who as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>had forſaken him and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced this preſent world.</hi> And indeed this Contagion ſpread ſo faſt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed ſo much, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> complain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſaying, <hi>all ſeek their own, and not the things of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Phil. 2.21.</p>
            <p>Thus having given you an account of the Riſe of the Falſe Teachers in the Apoſtles days, I ſhall now give you a more particular and full account of their deſign. And their <hi>Deſign</hi> as I have already intimated, was <hi>worldly:</hi> it was to <hi>Secure</hi> and <hi>Procure a worldly corrupt intereſt.</hi> It is not unlikely but that at the firſt their deſign in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying ſo much as they did with the profeſt enemies of Chriſtianity, was only to <hi>avoid</hi> thoſe ſufferings for the Goſpel ſake, which the ſincere Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians were expoſed to and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>went, both in their perſons and eſtates. But afterwards when they had carried away many by their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66155:15"/>and were become the Head and ring-leaders of a Party; a farther worldly advantage offered it ſelf and came in proſpect, (which we may well conceive they were not ſo dull as not to perceive, nor ſo careleſs and neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent as not to purſue) and that was an opportunity of <hi>Gain,</hi> of making <hi>merchandize</hi> of the ſeduced Chriſtians; (beſides the opportunity of gratifying their <hi>ambition</hi> in becoming the Head of a Party.) As the falſe Prophets of old, and the corrupt Prieſts, when by propheſying and preaching pleaſing things to the people, they found no ſmall benefit in the liberal gifts and rewards that courſe did procure, were encouraged to make a trade of ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (in which reſpect thoſe Prophets were ſaid <hi>to divine for money,</hi> and thoſe Prieſts <hi>to teach for hire:</hi>) even ſo the falſe Apoſtles alſo perceiving that to be a thriving way, applyed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to preach for Doctrine ſuch things as pleaſed the unſound and ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous profeſſors of the Goſpel, and ſo made their carnal ends on them.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66155:15"/>
               <hi>They taught things which they ought not, for filthy lucre ſake,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, and thereby <hi>ſubverted whole houſes, Tit.</hi> 1.11. They found that the preaching ſuch looſe Doctrine in point of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance as tended to eaſe the profeſſors of Chriſtianity of the burden of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution, was very <hi>gainful;</hi> it gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them many Proſelytes, for they came in by <hi>whole houſholds</hi> we ſee; and it gained them much of filthy lucre al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. For their Proſelytes grew very kind to them for teaching them an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſier and ſafer way of profeſſing Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity than they knew before. Yea, ſo it was that the poor deluded peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple became ſo much their ſervants up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on account of that ſatisfaction they took in that new diſcovery, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> upbraided ſome of them with it in theſe words: <hi>Ye ſuffer if a man bring you into bondage, if a man devour you, if a man take of you, if a man exalt himſelf, if a man ſmite you on the face,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.20.</p>
            <p>The deſign of theſe men to be a worldly and fleſhly deſign, is plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66155:16"/>as well as plainly diſcovered in the Epiſtles of the Apoſtles. The ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Chriſtians indeed ventured all their worldly concerns, and ſacrificed all their worldly intereſt upon the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Goſpel, their holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and their own Souls: but theſe men as St. <hi>Paul</hi> characteriſeth them, were <hi>enemies to the Croſs of Chriſt,</hi> they were ſuch as made <hi>their belly their God,</hi> and <hi>minded earthly things,</hi> Phil. 3.18, 19. They were enemies to the great duty of taking up the Croſs and ſuffering for Chriſt, earthly things having more of their heart than he had. Theſe who by their pleaſing doctrine aforeſaid, cauſed diviſions and offences among the Chriſtians, contrary to the Doctrine which they had learned from the true Apoſtles, were ſuch as <hi>ſerved not the Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> whatever they pretended, <hi>but their own bellies,</hi> Rom. 16.17, 18. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> deſcribing them, ſaith, <hi>they had hearts exerciſed with covetous practiſes, having for ſaken the right way, and going aſtray, followed the way of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66155:16"/>Balaam the ſon of Boſor who loved the wages of unrighteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.14, 15. <hi>They ran greedily after the way of Balaam for reward,</hi> as <hi>Jude</hi> hath it, verſ. 11. <hi>And through covetouſneſs with feigned words, they made merchandiſe of the people,</hi> whom they deluded, 2 Pet. 2.3.</p>
            <p>Now in caſe of Perſecution, 'tis true indeed that when Chriſt ſent forth his Diſciples as Sheep among Wolves; he adviſed them to <hi>be wiſe as Serpents, but innocent as Doves:</hi> to uſe as much prudence for the avoiding of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as would conſiſt with innocency, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.16. And no doubt but that the ſincereſt Chriſtians were willing enough to make uſe of all the prudence they had to ſhun perſecution ſo far as lawfully they might. But yet were ſtill careful to preſerve and maintain their own innocency and integrity in all they did in that kind, and not in the leaſt to betray the Cauſe of Chriſt: And therefore they could ſay in thoſe ſuffering times; <hi>This is our rejoycing, the teſtimony of our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:66155:17"/>that in ſimplicity and Godly ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, not with fleſhly wiſdom</hi> (as the falſe Apoſtles) <hi>but by the Grace of God we have had our converſation in the world,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.12. But the falſe Apoſtles and their followers, uſed ſo much ſubtilty and carnal policy to avoid the Croſs, as that the wiſdom of the Serpent did devour the innocency of the Dove. They made themſelves <hi>friends of the world</hi> indeed by unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful compliance, and by <hi>adulterating</hi> the Chriſtian Religion by impure mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: but then they thereby made themſelves <hi>enemies to God,</hi> as St. <hi>James</hi> ſaith, in betraying his Truth and Cauſe, <hi>James</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p>By the way then we may ſee by what hath been ſaid, how dangerous a thing it is inordinately to deſire and love the friendſhip of the world &amp; the accommodations of this preſent life: it is we ſee that which hath betrayed multitudes, otherwiſe in a hopeful way of Salvation, into curſed and deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Practiſes. <hi>They that will be rich fall into temptation and a ſnare, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66155:17"/>into many fooliſh and hurtful luſts, which drown men in deſtruction and perdition: for the love of money is the root of all evil: which while ſome coveted after, they have been ſeduced from the Faith, and pierced themſelves through with many ſorrows,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> ſpeaking of thoſe corrupt Chriſtians whoſe inordinate love to the things of this world, drew them into ſuch ſinful Compliances to preſerve them, as were inconſiſtent with Chriſtianity in the truth and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9, 10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Love not the world nor the things of the world,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John</hi> to thoſe who were in danger of being corrupted by the falſe Apoſtles through love to the world: <hi>for if any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him. For all that is in the world, the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eye, and the pride of life, is not of the Father but is of the world,</hi> 1 John 2.15, 16. Here's a brief deſcription of that love of the world which is diſallowed by God and a ſnare of death to men. The luſt of the Eye is covetouſneſs; which is a
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:66155:18"/>tranſgreſſion of the rule of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or moderation in deſiring or get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; or the rule of Piety or Charity in keeping the things of this world. The luſt of the Fleſh is a tranſgreſſing of the Laws of Sobriety, Temperance and Chaſtity, in uſing them: And the pride of Life is, a tranſgreſſion of the Laws of Modeſty and Humility in uſing undue means to draw honour and eſteem from men. Now then when St. <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>if any man love the world, the love of the Father is not in him,</hi> his meaning ſeems to be this; that when any man lives in the breach of any of Gods Commandments, in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veting, Getting, Keeping, or Uſing the things of this world; that's the man that ſo loves the world, as that the love of the Father is not in him. For as the love of God, according to this Apoſtle, conſiſteth in keeping his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as he ſaith, Chap. 5.3. <hi>This is the love of God, that we keep his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments;</hi> So the not loving the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but the world, conſiſts in the breach of his Commandments, in Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veting,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66155:18"/>Getting, Keeping, or Uſing the friendſhip or the things of the world. And thus the falſe Apoſtles were lovers of the world. They were willing to be for God and the Goſpel, ſo long and ſo far as their being ſo did not deprive them of their worldly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodations; but wherein it did, ſo that they could no longer <hi>ſerve two Maſters, God and Mammon,</hi> without faultering with one of them; then and in thoſe particular caſes when ſuch a Competition did occur, they were wont ſtill to cleave to their worldly intereſt, but to turn their back upon God and the Goſpel. For which cauſe they were compared to <hi>Eſau,</hi> and ſtiled prophane perſons like him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.16. For as <hi>Eſau</hi> preferred ſo inconſiderable a thing as a meſs of Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, becauſe of the <hi>preſentneſs</hi> of the ſatisfaction he expected thereby, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the far more deſirable priviledges and benefits of Birth-right and Heir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, becauſe they for a great part at leaſt were not to be received till <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards:</hi> So theſe lovers of, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigners
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:66155:19"/>for this preſent world, did chuſe eaſe and other worldly accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modations, becauſe <hi>preſent,</hi> rather than the better hope of eternal life, becauſe <hi>abſent and to come.</hi> This was the root of bitterneſs in the perſons of Seducers, againſt the ſpringing up of which among the Chriſtians, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of this Epiſtle had cautioned them, v. 15. At that time when the caſe was ſo, that <hi>all that would live god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in Chriſt Jeſus muſt ſuffer perſecution,</hi> there was no way of retaining a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Chriſtianity and their world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eaſe and enjoyments too, but by corrupting the Chriſtian Religion, and making it another thing than the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of it had made it; which was the thing the falſe Apoſtles laboured to bring the Chriſtians to, under delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive pretences, that they might ſave themſelves from ſuffering: which brings me to what is next to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſed, and that is to ſhew how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily theſe falſe Teachers corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Chriſtian Religion to attain their worldly end and baſe deſign.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:66155:19"/>
            <p>S. 2. The next thing then which, as I ſaid, I propoſed to ſhew, was how, in what way, and by what means the falſe Apoſtles carried on their world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſign, of which I have been ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: how in particular they ordered things in their profeſſion of Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſo as to ſecure their end, and to ſerve their deſign for this world. In doing of which I ſhall ſhew firſt, that to this end they <hi>corrupted</hi> the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion by their ſinful mixtures. Secondly, that they did this, and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on their whole deſign for the world under a <hi>Religious pretence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt they corrupted the Chriſtian Religion on purpoſe to ſerve their deſign. They corrupted it partly by adding other things to it which were of a contrary nature; and partly by ſiniſter and corrupt interpretations of the Chriſtian Doctrine, and of the Scriptures of the Old Teſtament, to countenance thoſe additions, either as <hi>lawful,</hi> or as <hi>neceſſary.</hi> And thus they abuſed the Scriptures touching the uſe of the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> by miſconſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:66155:20"/>and miſapplication. They would be eſteemed for judicious <hi>teachers of the Law, when they underſtood not what they ſaid; nor whereof they affirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.7. They taught Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion and the obſervation of other Rites of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the Salvation of Chriſtian Gentiles, when their doing ſo ſerved their carnal deſign, though otherwiſe they made no conſcience of keeping the Law themſelves. <hi>For neither they themſelves who are circumciſed keep the Law; but deſire to have you circumciſed that they may glory in your fleſh,</hi> ſaid St. <hi>Paul</hi> of them, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.13. but more of this afterwards. St. <hi>Peter</hi> alſo tells us that they wreſted things in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles, and other Scriptures to their own deſtruction. <hi>They walked in craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs and handled the word deceitfully,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> reflects it upon them, in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.2. and ſo he doth again when he ſaith, <hi>we are not as many which cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt the word of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 2.17. By an unkindly violence which they of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to it, they made it ſeemingly,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:66155:20"/>and in the eyes of weak and injudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and credulous perſons, to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance what they did in proſecution of their carnal deſign. And although theſe falſe appearances were but <hi>ſlight,</hi> and ſuch as had nothing ſatisfying in them to an unprejudiced and diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mind, yet they would ſerve for <hi>demonſtrations</hi> and paſs for good proof with thoſe who were willing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous to have thoſe things prove true, which the falſe Apoſtles pretended to be ſo. Like as when the falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets of old <hi>propheſied falſly, the people loved to have it ſo,</hi> becauſe it was for their carnal intereſt to have that prove true which they propheſied. But this only in general.</p>
            <p>But to come more particularly to the buſineſs, and to ſhew how they corrupted the Chriſtian Religion to ſave them from ſuffering, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs their farther ends. The ſincere Chriſtians were in great danger of ſuffering the loſs of all the things of this world for Chriſt and the Goſpel ſake, from two ſorts of enemies to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66155:21"/>Chriſtianity, the unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> and the unbelieving <hi>Gentiles.</hi> To avoid which, the Falſe Apoſtles taught themſelves firſt, and others after, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what to <hi>comply</hi> with theſe Enemies of Chriſtianity, in <hi>mixing</hi> ſomewhat of their Rites and Uſages with it, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to take off the edge of that Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition and Perſecution they before ſuffered from them, and by degrees thereby to reconcile them to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and to their Religion.</p>
            <p>This Device of theirs occaſion'd thoſe jealous apprehenſions St. <hi>Paul</hi> had of the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> after the Falſe Apoſtles got among them, which he thus expreſſeth, in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2, 3. <hi>I am jealous over you with godly jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie: for I have eſpouſed you to one husband, that I may preſent you as a chaſt virgin to Chriſt. But I fear leſt by any means, as the ſerpent beguiled Eve through his ſubtilty, ſo your minds ſhould be corrupted from the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. 3. Firſt, for the unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:66155:21"/>they, we know, were fierce Enemies againſt all that profeſſed the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Religion, labouring to raiſe Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution againſt them every where. To take off the edge of which, as I ſaid, the Falſe Apoſtles became Factors for <hi>Judaiſm,</hi> and ſo fell to perſwade the believing <hi>Gentiles</hi> to mix and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound <hi>Judaiſm</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as an Expedient both to ſave themſelves from Perſecution, and to win their Adverſaries to a liking of Chriſtianity. Of this attempt we read in <hi>Acts</hi> 15.1. <hi>Certain men which came down from Judea taught the brethren, and ſaid, Except ye be circumciſed af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the manner of Moſes, ye cannot be ſaved.</hi> And again, <hi>ver.</hi> 5. <hi>There aroſe certain of the ſect of the Phariſees, which believed, ſaying, That it was needful to circumciſe them, and to command them to keep the law of Moſes.</hi> That ſuch a thing as this was done, to avoid Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution from the <hi>Jews,</hi> appears from <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.12, 13. <hi>As many as make a fair ſhew in the fleſh, they conſtrain you to be circumciſed, onely leſt they ſhould
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:66155:22"/>ſuffer perſecution for the croſs of Chriſt.</hi> That they did it not ſo much out of Conſcience, as for this politick end, appears by <hi>ver.</hi> 13. <hi>For neither they themſelves who are circumciſed keep the law, but deſire to have you circumciſed, that they may glory in your fleſh,</hi> as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving now made them as well Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> way, as before they were to <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this way of compliance in the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> with the <hi>Jews,</hi> was effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al to ſecure them from Perſecution from the <hi>Jews,</hi> appears likewiſe from <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.11. <hi>And I, brethren, if I yet preach circumciſion, then is the offence of the croſs ceaſed.</hi> Upon this account doubtleſs it was, that ſome corrupt <hi>Chriſtians</hi> pretended themſelves to <hi>be Jews, who were not, but were of the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue of Satan,</hi> as we read <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3.9.</p>
            <p>Now this way of joyning and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mixing <hi>Judaiſm</hi> and <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſet on foot by falſe Teachers, under the Pretences aforeſaid, took dangerouſly among Profeſſors of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity;</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:66155:22"/>which was the occaſion of thoſe large Diſcourſes touching Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication by Faith, without the Works of the Law, which we have in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles both to the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Galatians.</hi> The plain meaning of which was, That the obſervation of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> way, was not neceſſary to Salvation in <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> as the falſe Apoſtles had taught it to be; and that it was unneceſſary for the <hi>Gentile</hi> Believers to be brought over to it; and that the Religion re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed and preſcribed in the Goſpel, called <hi>The Faith,</hi> and this alone, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out adding <hi>Judaiſm</hi> to it, was both ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and ſufficient to Salvation. And, by the way, thoſe that from the Apoſtles Reaſoning hereabout, would oppoſe the Works of Evangelical Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Faith, in the Point of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication, do greatly miſtake the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle in his deſign and way of Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>S. 2. Secondly, the falſe Teachers, to avoid Perſecution, and the loſs of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66155:23"/>all for the Goſpels ſake, from the <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> or unbelieving <hi>Gentiles,</hi> ſtruck in with them alſo in part, and taught the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that it was lawful for them to comply with their Idolatrous Neighbours, ſo far as to go with them to their Idol-feaſts, and to eat things ſacrificed to Idols, ſo long as they did not <hi>intentionally,</hi> and in their minds, do it in any honour to the Idol, but kept their mind to God. Some ſuch as theſe were in the Church of <hi>Pergamos, Revel.</hi> 2.14. <hi>I have a few things againſt thee, becauſe thou haſt there them that hold the doctrine of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam, who taught Balac to caſt a ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling-block before the children of Iſrael, to eat things ſacrificed to Idols, and to commit fornication.</hi> Such alſo were in the Church of <hi>Thyatira,</hi> ver. 20. <hi>I have a few things againſt thee, becauſe thou ſuffereſt that woman Jezabel, which calleth her ſelf a Propheteſs, to teach and ſeduce my ſervants to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit fornication, and to eat things ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed unto Idols.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That this was taught and practiſed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66155:23"/>as lawful, ſo long as it was not done intentionally to honour or worſhip the Idol, as the Infidels did, I gather from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Diſcourſe in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. In <hi>ver.</hi> 1. he ſaith, <hi>Now as touching things offered to Idols, we know that we all have knowledge.</hi> Knowledge of what? This he delivers more expreſly in <hi>ver.</hi> 4. <hi>We know that an Idol is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the world, and that there is none other God but one.</hi> This it ſeems was that which they pleaded in juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of their Practice of going to the Idols Temple, and of eating of things ſacrificed to the Idols: They <hi>knew</hi> that the Idol was nothing, and therefore did not <hi>intend</hi> any worſhip to it in what they did. The Apoſtle ſuppoſeth this to be true, and grants indeed, that they, and all Perſons generally, that owned the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Faith, did know that an Idol is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and that there is no other God but one, and that therefore probably ſuch could not be ſuppos'd to eat of the Idol-ſacrifice with intent to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Idol: But yet this Knowledge
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66155:24"/>was not <hi>univerſal,</hi> among all without exception, that had begun to own <hi>Chriſtianity;</hi> as he ſhews in <hi>ver.</hi> 7. ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Howbeit there is not in every man that knowledge: for ſome with conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Idol unto this hour eat it as a thing offered unto an Idol, and their conſcience being weak is defiled.</hi> And ſo argues the unlawfulneſs of their Practice, upon the account of <hi>ſcandal</hi> to weak Brethren, to the end of the Chapter. But in the tenth Chapter, where he reaſſumes this Buſineſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, he argues plainly, That whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their knowledge or intention was, yet that by that Practice they had communion with the Idol or Devils, to whom indeed the Offering was made. See from <hi>ver.</hi> 14. to <hi>ver.</hi> 22.</p>
            <p>It was for this Seduction by falſe Teachers, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> do ſo earneſtly inveigh againſt them, as <hi>following the way of Balaam for reward,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. <hi>Jude</hi> 11. And <hi>Balaams</hi> way, we know, was to teach <hi>Balac</hi> to draw the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to Idolatry and Whoredom, by enticing them to eat
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66155:24"/>with the <hi>Moabites</hi> of their Idol-ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 31.16. And it was againſt this Seduction by falſe Teachers, that St. <hi>John</hi> admoniſhed the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> when in the cloſe of his firſt Epiſtle he ſaid, <hi>Little children keep your ſelves from Idols.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How far this device of ſinful com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with Unbelievers, both of <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles,</hi> did ſucceed to draw them over to them, to become ſuch <hi>Christians</hi> as themſelves, I know not; which yet doubtleſs was one thing they promiſed themſelves in it: yet it's very probable they found by experience, that their complying with the <hi>Heathen,</hi> in going to their Idol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feaſts, did procure them much eaſe, as their compliance with the <hi>Jews</hi> had done, either in freeing them from, or greatly abating that Perſecution, which before they were expoſed unto by profeſſing the Goſpel; which was another thing they promiſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in it. And there are two things eſpecially which make this probable. The one is, in that this Device of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66155:25"/>Compliance took with the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and prevailed ſo much in the ſeveral Churches, as by the Scriptutes alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy quoted we ſee it did. The other is, in that St. <hi>Paul</hi> brings in the <hi>Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians</hi> applauding themſelves in their happy condition, ſince the time their new Teachers came among them, to teach them a more eaſie and ſafe way of profeſſing the Goſpel, than <hi>Paul</hi> had done, in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8, 10. <hi>Now ye are full, now ye are rich, ye have reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as kings without us: We are fools for Chriſts ſake, but ye are wiſe in Chriſt: we are weak, but ye are ſtrong: ye are honourable, but we are deſpiſed: even unto this preſent hour, we both hunger, and thirſt, are naked, and buf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feted, &amp;c.</hi> They had Halcyon days now, as they thought, in compariſon of what they had before. And it appears, that this Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> eſpecially, was infected with this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagious Diſeaſe, in that St. <hi>Paul</hi> hath it ſo often up, arguing againſt it, warning them of it ſeveral times, and in both his Epiſtles to them. And
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:66155:25"/>the eaſe they found by it, was in all likelihood, as I ſaid, the temptation by which it prevail'd ſo much among them as it did.</p>
            <p>S. 5. Other things alſo they did, in <hi>corrupting</hi> the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Religion, to <hi>ingratiate</hi> themſelves with the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of it; whereof <hi>Worſhipping of Angels</hi> I may name for one, againſt which the Apoſtle warned the <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> in <hi>Col.</hi> 2.18. ſaying, <hi>Let no man beguile you of your reward, in a volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary humility and worſhipping of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, intruding into thoſe things which he hath not ſeen, vainly puft up with his fleſhly mind.</hi> Whether this was done and taught in compliance with thoſe <hi>Heathen</hi> who followed the way of <hi>Platonick</hi> Philoſophy in this, as ſome think; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> had ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, in <hi>ver.</hi> 8. <hi>Beware leſt any man ſpoil you through Philoſophy and vain deceit:</hi> or whether to draw near to the <hi>Pagans,</hi> who had their <hi>Daemons,</hi> their <hi>Baalims,</hi> or Lords, to whom they addreſſed themſelves as Mediators to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:66155:26"/>their Superiour Deities, I ſhall not determine: But I think there is little queſtion to be made, but that this their falling back to the Rudiments of the World, as well as other their Sophiſtications, was to ſerve them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their worldly deſign.</p>
            <p>S. 6. Furthermore, They denied the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of the Body, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with the Enemies of <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi> The <hi>Pagans,</hi> and likewiſe the <hi>Sadduces,</hi> which were a prevailing Sect among the <hi>Jews,</hi> held no Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the Body after death. And we find that this Heretical Opinion was ſet on foot in the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> by ſome among them, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.12. <hi>How ſay ſome among you, that there is no reſurrection of the dead?</hi> And we have little reaſon but to think, that thoſe who did put it on foot there, did ſo, the more to curry favour with the Oppoſers and Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> who profeſt a belief of the Doctrine of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection; becauſe that for the ſame
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:66155:26"/>reaſon they did unduely comply with them in other things, as I have ſhewed. And becauſe this was ſo manifeſtly contrary to the Goſpel, which yet they profeſt, that in denying that, they did in effect deny the Goſpel; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to bring themſelves off from this ſelf contradiction in their Profeſſion, when they felt themſelves hard preſt with it, they fell to quibling with this Doctrine of the Reſurrection, and to put <hi>myſtical</hi> Interpretations upon it, (as ſome in our days have done) <hi>ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, That the reſurrection was paſt alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> as <hi>Hymeneus and Philetus</hi> did, in 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.17, 18. They taught it ſeems, That what is ſo oft affirmed in the Goſpel touching the Reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, was to be underſtood of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection then already paſt.</p>
            <p>S. 7. Again, To <hi>increaſe</hi> their Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and to <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> their Intereſt, they broached Doctrines of Liberti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſm and Licentiouſneſs, which is a courſe that uſually proves too ſucceſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful in drawing corrupt Men to be on
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66155:27"/>the ſide of ſuch Teachers, and for the ſake thereof, to eſpouſe other of their Opinions. Such Men will run after ſuch Teachers, <hi>heaping to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>teachers after their own luſts,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3. St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking of this courſe of theirs, in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18, 19. ſaith, <hi>When they ſpeak great ſwelling words of vanity, they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure through the luſts of the fleſh thoſe who were clean eſcaped from thoſe who live in errour: While they promiſe them liberty, they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption.</hi> As in the things before-mentioned they corrupted the <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> Religion in point of <hi>Worſhip;</hi> ſo in this, under conſideration, they cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted it in point of <hi>Manners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fornication</hi> was held a thing law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful among the <hi>Gentiles</hi> (<hi>Acts</hi> 15.29.) and the falſe Teachers, to make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Friends of the World, taught the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> to eſteem it lawful too, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.20. <hi>Thou ſuffereſt the woman Jezabel, who calleth her ſelf a prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs, to teach and to ſeduce my ſervants to commit fornication, &amp;c.</hi> And ſo
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66155:27"/>again, in <hi>ver.</hi> 14, 15. <hi>Thou haſt them that hold the doctrine of Balaam, &amp;c. ſo haſt thou alſo them that hold the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the Nicolaitans, which thing I hate.</hi> This ſort of Men <hi>had eyes full of adultery, beguiling unſtable ſouls,</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.14. <hi>They crept into houſes, and led captive ſilly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, laden with ſins, and led away with divers luſts,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p>They taught it alſo to be lawful to caſt off <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Subjection</hi> to Governours, both Maſters and Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, under pretence of their <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Liberty</hi> by the Goſpel; which was a Doctrine very taking with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, eſpecially <hi>Jews,</hi> many of whom were otherwiſe of themſelves, upon all occaſions, forward enough to caſt off the <hi>Roman</hi> yoke. Upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count theſe Seducers were ſaid to <hi>deſpiſe government, and to ſpeak evil of dignities,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.10. Jude 11. <hi>And to periſh in the gainſaying of Core,</hi> who, as we know, oppoſed <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> in their Government. Againſt this Seduction St. <hi>Peter</hi> cautions the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:66155:28"/>
               <hi>Christians,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.16, 17. when he ſaith, <hi>As free, and not uſing your li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty as a cloak of maliciouſneſs, but as the ſervants of God. Honour all men. Love the brotherhood. Fear God. Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King.</hi> And ſo doth St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.1. <hi>Let as many ſervants as are under the yoke, count their own ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters worthy of all honour, that the Name of God and his Doctrine be not bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. 8. Furthermore, they grew to this at laſt, that if all their other Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances would not ſecure them from ſuffering Perſecution for owning the Name of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they taught, That then, in caſe of neceſſity, and before a Judge, it was lawful, and matter of liberty, to <hi>deny Chriſt in word,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided they did but <hi>inwardly</hi> retain a belief in him in their hearts. Of theſe St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks, ſaying, <hi>There ſhall be falſe teachers among you, who privily ſhall bring in damnable hereſies, even denying the Lord that bought them,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.1. And St. <hi>Jude</hi> ſaith, <hi>ver.</hi> 4.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66155:28"/>
               <hi>That there were certain men crept in unawares, turning the grace of God in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to laſciviouſneſs, and denying the onely Lord God, and our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus we ſee how the falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and their Followers, by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with the unbelieving <hi>Jews</hi> on the one hand, and <hi>Gentiles</hi> on the other, corrupted the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, out of a carnal worldly deſign, quite contrary to the Doctrine and Practice of the true Apoſtles, whoſe Exhortation, as they ſaid, <hi>was not of deceit, nor of uncleanneſs, nor in guile,</hi> as the others was; <hi>but as they were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of God to be put in truſt with the Goſpel, even ſo they ſpake, not as plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing men,</hi> as the other did, <hi>but God, which tried their hearts. Neither at any time uſed they flattering words, nor a cloak of covetouſneſs,</hi> as the other did, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.3, 4, 5.</p>
            <p>S. 9. But poſſibly this may riſe in the minds of ſome, as an Objection, That St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf did in many things <hi>comply</hi> both with the <hi>Jews</hi> and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66155:29"/>
               <hi>Gentiles.</hi> For doth not he himſelf ſay, <hi>That unto the Jews I became as a Jew, that I might gain the Jews; to them that are under the Law, as under the Law, that I might gain them that are under the Law; to them that are without Law, as without Law, to gain them that are without Law; and that he became all things to all men,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.20, 21? And if <hi>Paul</hi> were not to blame in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, how came the other to be ſo faulty by reaſon of their compliances? But, in anſwer to this, let it be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, that the difference between the compliance of St. <hi>Paul</hi> and that of the falſe Apoſtles, was vaſtly great.</p>
            <p>Firſt in the <hi>end</hi> of it, The govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing end of the falſe Apoſtles in their compliance, was <hi>earthly, worldly, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> as I have ſhewed: but the end of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his, was purely <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> it was for the furtherance of the Goſpel and mens ſalvation thereby. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from that place, and thoſe very words from which the objection is raiſed. When he became as a <hi>Jew</hi> to the <hi>Jews, it was to gain the Jews:</hi> and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:66155:29"/>when he became as without Law to them that were without Law, <hi>it was to gain them:</hi> And, as it follows in the 22. and 23. Verſes, <hi>I am made all things to all men, that I might by all means ſave ſome: and this I do,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for the Goſpels ſake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, The difference was vaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly great in the <hi>nature</hi> of their compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance as well as in the end. The falſe Apoſtles complied with the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in the Rites of their worſhip and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of manners, to the apparent <hi>breach</hi> of the Laws of God, the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt, and precepts of the Goſpel. But St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his compliance with them went not at all <hi>beyond thoſe holy bounds.</hi> For he ſaith, that when he was as without Law to them that were without Law, yet he was not therein <hi>without Law to God, but under the Law to Christ,</hi> ver. 21. It's true, the falſe Apoſtles or their Proſelytes, did report of <hi>Paul</hi> (and it's like it was from his compliance for the Goſpel ſake that they did ſo) <hi>that he ſhould ſay, Let us do evil that good may come,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:66155:30"/>but St. <hi>Paul</hi> rejected it as a <hi>ſlanderous report</hi> of them whoſe damnation is juſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. They really did it themſelves, but would have faſtened it upon him.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s being as without Law to the Gentiles which were without the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> was but his <hi>encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> and <hi>ſtrengthning</hi> them in that opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that there was no need that the believing Gentiles ſhould be circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed or keep the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as ſome would have had them: <hi>And he blamed Peter as not walking uprightly according to the truth of the Goſpel, when he did otherwiſe, and compelled the Gentiles to live as did the Jews,</hi> Gal. 2.14.</p>
            <p>And then as for <hi>Paul</hi>'s becoming as a Jew to the Jews that he might gain the Jews; it's true, when he ſaw that his indulging the uſe of the Jewiſh Rites only among the Jews, as things <hi>lawful</hi> but not <hi>neceſſary,</hi> would further the ſucceſs of the Goſpel in propagat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Chriſtian Religion among them, he <hi>yielded</hi> to them therein, as in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:66155:30"/>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 21. And for the ſame cauſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed <hi>Timothy:</hi> for his Mother be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Jeweſs, and <hi>Paul</hi> having a mind to have him go forth with him in the work of the Goſpel, he took and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed him becauſe of the Jews which were in thoſe quarters, who otherwiſe would probably have op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that undertaking, or at leaſt would not have accepted of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.3.</p>
            <p>But the falſe Apoſtles to <hi>pacifie</hi> and to <hi>gratifie</hi> the Jews who raiſed perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution againſt <hi>Paul</hi> and others for tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the believing Gentiles into an equality with the believing Jews, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being circumciſed, did teach that it was <hi>neceſſary</hi> that the believing Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſhould be circumciſed, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and that they could not be ſaved without it, as I ſhewed before. And in this St. <hi>Paul</hi> was ſo far from complying with the Jews, as the falſe Apoſtles did, that he ſtrenuouſly <hi>oppoſed</hi> them in it, teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying to thoſe believing Gentiles that were in this enſnared by the falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66155:31"/>or in great danger of being ſo, ſaying, <hi>Behold, I Paul ſay unto you, that if ye be circumciſed, Christ ſhall profit you nothing,</hi> Gal. 5.2. And again, ver. 4. <hi>Chriſt is become of none effect unto you, whoſoever of you are juſtified by the Law, ye are fallen from grace.</hi> And therefore when ſome of theſe <hi>falſe brethren were privily and unawares brought in to ſpie out the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> which was uſed in owning and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the Gentiles without Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, and to try if they could bring them into <hi>bondage</hi> by procuring <hi>Titus,</hi> who was a <hi>Greek,</hi> to be Circumciſed; St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>That to theſe they did not give place, no not for an hour, that the truth of the Goſpel might continue with them,</hi> Gal. 2.3, 4, 5. Implying plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that ſuch a complyance with the Jews in yielding <hi>Titus</hi> a Gentile to be Circumciſed, conſidering the <hi>circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances</hi> under which the falſe Apoſtles urged the Circumciſion of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, would have tended to a <hi>corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of the Goſpel in the minds of the Chriſtians, and have miniſtred an
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66155:31"/>
               <hi>advantage</hi> to the falſe Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>And now I ſuppoſe it appears that the compliance in <hi>Paul</hi> with the Jews and Gentiles, differed as much both in the nature and end of it from the compliance of the falſe Apoſtles, as Vice and Virtue differ. And that they did differ, the falſe Apoſtles un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood well enough, and therefore hated <hi>Paul</hi> and the ſincere Chriſtians as their oppoſites, and joined with their perſecutors in perſecuting of them; ſtill the more to ingratiate themſelves with them. Theſe were of thoſe, as I ſuppoſe, that, St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Preached Chriſt of envy and ſtrife, of contention, and not ſincerely, ſuppoſing to add affliction to his bonds,</hi> Phil. 1.15, 16. Of theſe it was, as I appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend by the ſcope of the place, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid; <hi>But as then he that was born after the fleſh, perſecuted him that was born after the ſpirit, even ſo it is now,</hi> Gal. 4.29. Of theſe St. <hi>John</hi> ſpeaks, as I take it, when he ſaith, <hi>He that ſaith he is in the light, and hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his brother, is in darkneſs until now,</hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:66155:32"/>1 John 2.9. and cautions the brethren that they <hi>be not as Cain,</hi> as ſome falſe Chriſtians were, <hi>who ſlew his brother becauſe his own works were evil and his brothers righteous,</hi> 1 John 3.12.</p>
            <p>S. 10. Having ſhewed how the Chriſtian Religion was corrupted by the falſe Apoſtles on purpoſe to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote their ſecular deſign, I might now ſhew yet a little further, how lamentably the Apoſtolical Churches were in a little time over-run with it, and many of the Members thereof ſowred with this Leaven, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> feared they would, when he ſaid in reference to thoſe corrupters, <hi>A little Leaven leaveneth the whole lump, and wiſheth that they were cut off that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled the Church,</hi> Gal. 5.7, 8, 9. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably this their being neither directly and wholly Chriſtian, nor Jew, nor Pagan, but a mixture of all, to keep fair quarter with all, was the crime of the Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> in being <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hot nor cold,</hi> neither fiſh nor fleſh, as we ſay, neither Chriſtian, Jew, nor
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66155:32"/>Pagan, but a compoſition of all toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and yet thought themſelves in a brave condition, <hi>rich and increaſed in goods and had need of nothing.</hi> Juſt as ſome of thoſe in the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> upon the ſame account thought themſelves to be, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> repreſents it in 1 Cor. 4.8. <hi>Now ye are full, now ye are rich, ye have reigned as Kings without us.</hi> They applauded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in that they had found out, as they thought, a wiſer way of being Chriſtians, than the Apoſtles and others had done: for they, as they thought, could hold the faith of the Goſpel, and their worldly enjoyments too. Whereas others which they thought more imprudent in profeſſing the Goſpel, expoſed themſelves to the ſpoiling of their Goods, and the loſs of all things. To ſuch as theſe it was, I conceive, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith thus, in 1 Cor. 3.18. <hi>Let no man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive himſelf: if any man among you ſeemeth to be wiſe in this world,</hi> (mark that, wiſe in this world) <hi>let him become a fool that he may be wiſe.</hi> That is, let
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:66155:33"/>him become ſuch a Chriſtian as thoſe who by a faithful and cloſe adherence to the doctrine and precepts of the Goſpel, expoſed themſelves to the loſs of all in this world, and were counted fools for ſo doing, by the falſe Apoſtles and their adherents; that he may be wiſe to purpoſe, wiſe for the world to come. So here, in <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.18. Chriſt in oppoſition to this carnal conceit of the <hi>Laodiceans</hi> of their being <hi>rich,</hi> counſels them to <hi>buy of him Gold tryed in the fire that they might be rich</hi> in deed, and not in conceit only. That is, as I conceive, that they would not <hi>ſhrink</hi> at the <hi>fiery tryal</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> calls it, which his faithful followers patiently endured for his ſake, and which being endur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed would make them ſpiritually <hi>rich</hi> indeed, <hi>rich</hi> in the experimental know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and proof of their own ſinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and fidelity to Chriſt; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>rich</hi> in their aſſurance of their title to the reward promiſed to thoſe that overcome; and conſequently <hi>rich</hi> alſo in that conſolation, peace, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66155:33"/>joy, which ſuch a knowledge and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience would furniſh them withal, far beyond all mens worldly enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments could afford them when pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved with their faultring and double dealing with Chriſt in their profeſſion of his Religion. <hi>For as the ſufferings of Chriſt abounded</hi> in his faithful fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, <hi>ſo their conſolation alſo abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him,</hi> as thoſe who experienced it did teſtifie, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. Who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>gloried in tribulations</hi> of that kind, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.3. And therefore well might St. <hi>Peter</hi> ſay, that this <hi>trial of faith,</hi> this proof of the goodneſs of faith, this ſpiritual gold, by enduring the fire, <hi>is much more precious than that of Gold that periſheth, though it be tried with fire,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.7. And proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably they are much more <hi>rich</hi> that have abundance of that, than they that have abundance of this.</p>
            <p>All this ſerves to demonſtrate the wiſdom and goodneſs of that counſel of Chriſt to the <hi>Laodiceans,</hi> to <hi>buy of him Gold tried in the fire</hi> that they might be <hi>rich,</hi> and not to decline doing ſo,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66155:34"/>that they might retain their worldly riches. And ſo doth that of buying of him <hi>white raiment to cover the ſhame of their nakedneſs.</hi> By which I under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, ſuch an outward converſation in divine worſhip &amp; manners, as is called by St. <hi>James,</hi> a being <hi>unſpotted of the world,</hi> and as is oppoſed to ſuch an one as is deſcribed by <hi>garments ſpotted by the fleſh,</hi> in S. <hi>Jude,</hi> of which ſome profeſſing Chriſtianity, were guilty by their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances with the Heathen in their evil cuſtoms, to curry their favors as well as to gratifie their own luſts. The other part of our Lords counſel to them was, to <hi>anoint their eyes with eye-ſalve that they might ſee,</hi> that is, make a right judgment of the nature of Chriſtianity, and <hi>ſee</hi> things <hi>a far off</hi> in the other world, to govern themſelves by their concernment in thoſe things, and not ſtill remain like thoſe who <hi>are blind and cannot ſee a far off,</hi> as St. <hi>Peter</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes them, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. but govern themſelves only by the ſenſe they have of preſent things, nigh unto them and juſt before them, as bruit beaſts
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:66155:34"/>do, to which they are compared in that reſpect, when it's ſaid; <hi>In what they know naturally as bruit beaſts, in thoſe things they corrupt themſelves,</hi> Jude verſ. 10. And by underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the meaning of this counſel of Chriſt to them, we may underſtand the nature of their diſeaſe to which this counſel was applied by way of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. Their great diſtemper lay in two things; Firſt, in their <hi>carnal com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance</hi> for fear of ſuffering: by reaſon of which compliance they were neither hot nor cold, neither thorow Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, nor thorow Pagans, nor Jews, as I ſaid, but like <hi>Ephraim</hi> of old, <hi>a Cake half baked, or a ſpeckled Bird</hi> of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral colours, to which <hi>Iſrael</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared in their declined condition. Secondly, in <hi>applauding</hi> themſelves in that they had by this means found out a way of being good Chriſtians, as they thought, without expoſing themſelves to ſuffering for it, and as if they had been in a happier condition than others that had not done ſo: Whenas by that means, and for that very reaſon,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66155:35"/>
               <hi>they were miſerable and poor, and blind, and naked,</hi> and loathſom to Chriſt, and ready to be <hi>ſpewed out of his mouth;</hi> far from ſuch a happy condition as they fancied themſelves to be in.</p>
            <p>This alſo, probably, was the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church of <hi>Sardis, Rev.</hi> 3.1. except <hi>the few names in it that had not defiled their Garments</hi> with thoſe pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions into which the falſe Teachers had enticed others. For though they <hi>had a name to live,</hi> from that profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Goſpel which they made, yet were in a manner <hi>dead,</hi> by dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerating and going back again in part into Gentiliſm or Judaiſm, from which they had been delivered.</p>
            <p>The <hi>loſs of firſt love</hi> in the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> alſo, as it's very likely, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell them by the deceiving of the falſe Teachers we ſpeak of, that drove a worldly deſign in profeſſing the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, ſo as that it might not be too coſtly to them. This St. <hi>Paul</hi> had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told, when he ſaid to the Elders of that Church, in Act. 20.29, 30. <hi>I know this, that after my departure ſhall grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66155:35"/>Wolves enter in among you, not ſparing the flock: alſo of your own ſelves ſhall men ariſe, ſpeaking perverſe things, to draw away Diſciples after them.</hi> And he admoniſhed them in his Epiſtle to them, Chap. 4.14. <hi>That they would be no more children toſſed to and fro, and carried about with every wind of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, by the ſlight of men and cunning craftineſs, whereby they lay in wait to deceive.</hi> And again, Chap. 5.6. <hi>Let no man deceive you with vain words,</hi> &amp;c. Meaning doubtleſs in all this, to arm them againſt, and take them off from the inſinuations &amp; temptations of falſe Teachers, to draw them into ſinful complyances to eſcape perſecution.</p>
            <p>Another hint of this nature we have in the cloſe of his Epiſtle to them, Chap. 6.24. where he ſaith, <hi>Grace be with all them that love our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity,</hi> or with <hi>incorrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as it is in the Margin: that is, without <hi>mixing</hi> his Religion with any thing foraign to it, or inconſiſtent with it, for worldly ends as ſome had done.</p>
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:66155:36"/>
            <p>Our Saviour in <hi>Revel.</hi> 2.3. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends them for that at firſt they <hi>had born and had patience to ſuffer, and for his names ſake had laboured and had not fainted.</hi> But then in the 5th. ver. he calls upon them to <hi>remember from whence they were fallen, and to repent and do their firſt works.</hi> They were now fallen from that love and zeal for Chriſt, which at firſt they manifeſted to him in ſuffering for him, called here their <hi>first love,</hi> which now they <hi>had lost:</hi> and had now found out an eaſier way, but withall an impurer way of owning Chriſt and profeſſing his Goſpel. Which change he admoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them to repent of, and to return to their firſt love and zeal in keeping cloſe to the truth and purity of the Chriſtian Religion, whatever the Iſſue of it might be as to this worlds concerns: for theſe were their <hi>firſt works,</hi> as appears by what was ſaid before of them in the 3d. verſ. And thoſe Chriſtians that kept to this whatever it coſt them, were ſuch as were ſaid to be <hi>Virgins, Virgin Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:66155:36"/>that had not violated their cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtity to Chriſt, but <hi>followed the Lamb</hi> only <hi>whitherſoever he went,</hi> though he led them through fire and water, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.3.</p>
            <p>I the rather think that corrupt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliances through fear of ſuffering, were the faults of thoſe Five of theſe Seven Churches which came under reproof; becauſe that, for which the other Two of <hi>Smyrna</hi> and <hi>Philadelphia</hi> are commended and not cenſured at all, was their courage for, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in the truth of the Goſpel, in the midſt of danger, impoveriſhing and trouble, becauſe of it. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9, 10. <hi>I know thy works, and tribulation, and poverty, but thou art rich. Fear none of thoſe things which thou ſhalt ſuffer.</hi> Rev. 3.8.10. <hi>Thou haſt a little ſtrength, and haſt kept my word and haſt not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied my name. Becauſe thou haſt kept the word of my patience, I alſo will keep thee from the hour of temptation that ſhall come upon all the world to try them.</hi> Beſides, the promiſe in the cloſe of every one of the Seven Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:66155:37"/>made to him that overcometh, together with the other ſubject mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of them, argues that the being overcome and prevailed with to do unworthily through fear of ſuffering, was the ſin of ſome, and the temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dangerous to all of them.</p>
            <p>S. 11.2. Having ſhewed you how the falſe Apoſtles carried on their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of ſecuring their worldly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns in their profeſſion of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, by corrupting it: I ſhall now come to ſhew how they did it under a <hi>ſhow and pretence</hi> of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: which was the laſt thing I propoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to inſiſt on concerning them and their ill deſign. This courſe taken by them of ſetting off what they did herein with a ſhew and pretence of being very Religious in it, was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but what our Saviour had fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told would come to paſs, premoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Diſciples to take heed of being deceived hereby, when he ſaid, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of falſe Prophets which come to you in ſheeps clothing, but inwardly they are
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66155:37"/>ravening Wolves,</hi> Mat. 7.15. They could not carry on their deſign alone without making a party among them that profeſſed the Goſpel, nor that, but under a Religious pretence. And a party they did make to join with them in it, by ſuch means as I ſhall now briefly inſtance in.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They did it by obtaining the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation</hi> among many, of being the <hi>Miniſters of Christ,</hi> yea, perhaps of being the <hi>Apoſtles of Chriſt,</hi> which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſome of them pretended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be. Which was of great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to them; it being no hard matter for them to corrupt thoſe with whom they obtained ſuch a reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to draw them in to fide with them in their deſign. For when once the people came to eſteem them, the Miniſters and Meſſengers of Chriſt, as well as <hi>Paul</hi> and other Apoſtles; the falſe Apoſtles then came to have a great advantage thereby of drawing them off from thoſe that were the Miniſters of Chriſt indeed, and of bringing them under their own conduct; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:66155:38"/>their doctrine tended to ſecure them from that perſecution and loſs of worldly enjoyments, which the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the true Apoſtles, when fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, expoſed them to. And if the people could be brought to give as much credit to the doctrine of the falſe Apoſtles as to that of the true, as they muſt if they believed them to be true Apoſtles, though they were not: then they could be in no doubt which to follow, for they would then certainly follow them, who, as they believed, taught them how to keep this world, and yet obtain that which is to come too, rather than them who taught them to run almoſt a certain hazard of this, that they might obtain the next. And it was becauſe of this advantage, that they had the perſons of the falſe Apoſtles in admiration, <hi>Jude</hi> 16. Now that they pretended them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be the Miniſters of Chriſt, and not only ſo, but that they were eſteemed ſo to be by a party, appears by that of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> where he ſaith in his own vindication thus: <hi>Are they
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:66155:38"/>Miniſters of Chriſt? I am more,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.23. They preached Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith; but it was of <hi>envy, strife, and contention, not ſincere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuppoſing to add affliction to my bonds,</hi> Phil. 1.15, 16. They envied him the honour and reſpect he had among the Chriſtians, by preaching Chriſt and Salvation by him to them; and ſo they preached Chriſt and Salvation by him too; but yet in a way of oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to <hi>Paul,</hi> by preaching Chriſt <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſincerely, mixing</hi> other things with his doctrine, that were more gratifying to the fleſh, and thereby drawing off the reſpect of the Chriſtians from <hi>Paul</hi> to themſelves, which if effected, muſt needs add affliction to his bonds. <hi>They zealouſly affect you, but not well,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, yea they would exclude us that you might affect them,</hi> Gal. 4.17.</p>
            <p>And that they might not be thought inferiour to the Apoſtles of Chriſt, who were extraordinarily ſent, and of a higher ſtanding than any other in the Evangelical Miniſtry; they alſo, ſome of them, pretended themſelves to be
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:66155:39"/>the <hi>Apoſtles of Chriſt,</hi> that they might put the more glorious colour upon their deſign and arts of deceiving. <hi>Such are falſe Apoſtles, deceitful work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, transforming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.13. Nay, it ſhould ſeem ſome of them did not only pretend to an equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity with <hi>Paul,</hi> but alſo to a more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Apoſtolick authority than was in him. For they called St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Apoſtleſhip into queſtion, and ſought to undermine the reputation of his Apoſtolical authority. Upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and for this cauſe it was that <hi>Paul</hi> was conſtrained to vindicate his Apoſtleſhip to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> as he did in 1 <hi>Ep. Chap.</hi> 9. <hi>Ver.</hi> 1, 2. <hi>Am I not an Apoſtle? am I not free? have not I ſeen the Lord? are not you my work in the Lord? if I be not an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle to others, yet doubtleſs I am to you, for the Seal of my Apoſtleſhip are ye in the Lord.</hi> See farther for this, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 11.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 12.11, 12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13.3.6. They inſinuated that <hi>Paul</hi> had not <hi>ſeen Chriſt,</hi> as thoſe that were truly his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:66155:39"/>Apoſtles had, and that he had receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Goſpel which he preached, but <hi>from men</hi> and not immediately from Chriſt, and that therefore he might be miſtaken. In oppoſition to which, it was that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid; <hi>I certifie you brethren, that the Goſpel which was preached of me, is not after man: for I neither received it of men, neither was I taught it, but by the revelation of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 1.11, 12.</p>
            <p>But though too many were ſo weak as to be deceived with theſe mens great ſwelling words, yet there were others that were too wiſe to be impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon by their pretenſions to Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip. And ſuch were thoſe of the Church of <hi>Epheſus</hi> for a while at leaſt, till they fell from their firſt love. <hi>Thou haſt tried them which ſay they are Apoſtles, and are not, and haſt found them liars,</hi> ſaith Chriſt to the Angel of that Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2. As for ſuch as were deceived and did take them to be what they pretended themſelves to be, Apoſtles; and upon that account could give as much credit to what
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:66155:40"/>they ſaid, as to what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid: it was no marvel if they thought themſelves in a better condition by their coming among them, than they had been in by following <hi>Paul;</hi> in as much as they taught them an eaſier and cheaper way of being Chriſtians, than he had done, as I have often ſaid. And that they did think themſelves in a happier con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, appears by that repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their thoughts which St. <hi>Paul</hi> made when he ſaid, <hi>now ye are rich, now ye are full, ye have reigned as Kings without us,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.10.</p>
            <p>S. 12.2. And to gain yet the more credit among the Chriſtians, whom they laboured thereby to ſeduce, they pretended to <hi>promote the ends of</hi> the Goſpel, <hi>holineſs and righteouſneſs,</hi> in what they did and taught. For the Goſpel is ſo expreſs for theſe, that the profeſſors of it could hardly be cheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and corrupted in there profeſſion of it, but under a pretence of promot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing theſe. And therefore there is no queſtion but that theſe falſe Apoſtles
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:66155:40"/>talked as high for holineſs and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and made as great a noiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it in ſound of words and name of the thing in general terms (as ſeducers uſe to do) as the true Apoſtles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. And therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith <hi>that they transformed themſelves as the miniſters of righteouſneſs,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.15. They were for <hi>a form of godlineſs</hi> in profeſſion, though they <hi>denied it in the power</hi> and practice of it, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. They <hi>were wells and clouds without water,</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Jude</hi> deſcribe them? they in profeſſion promiſed the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of Religion and vertue, as wells promiſe water and clouds rain: but they were but as empty and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull wells and clouds in this.</p>
            <p>Nay they did not only pretend to holineſs and righteouſneſs as well as the true Apoſtles, but they pretended to <hi>more ſtrictneſs</hi> in ſome things than the Apoſtles themſelves. They pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to go farther in mortification and ſelf-denial, than the Apoſtles did, in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing upon themſelves and others ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence from ſome meats, and from
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66155:41"/>Marriage: <hi>forbidding them to marry and commanding them to abſtain from ſome meats,</hi> was part of the doctrine of theſe ſeducing Spirits. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.18. <hi>Touch not, taſt not, handle not,</hi> ſaid they: <hi>which things,</hi> ſaith St. Paul, <hi>have indeed a ſhew of wiſdom in will worſhip and humility, and neglecting of the body, not in any honour to the ſatisfying of the fleſh,</hi> Col. 2.21.23. They pretended that St. <hi>Paul</hi> and ſuch as he, walked but according to the fleſh, in compariſon of themſelves who lived a more abſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mious and mortified Life, as they would have others to think.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I think to be bold,</hi> ſaith St. Paul, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſome, who think of us as if we walked according to the fleſh,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.2. <hi>Let no man judge you,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>in meat or in drink, or in reſpect of an Holy day, or of the New Moon, or of the Sabbath dayes,</hi> Col. 2.16. They were for judging the Chriſtians that followed St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as not ſo tender and conſcientious about theſe things, as they themſelves pretended to be. For that we ſee hath been and indeed ſtill
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:66155:41"/>is the manner of Seducers, to pretend to great ſtrictneſs in ſome little things which are not neceſſary in themſelves; thereby to gain a great reputation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong people of weak minds, for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, mortification and ſtrictneſs of living, when in the mean time they are deeply culpable in other things of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the eyes of thoſe of more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Spirits. Like the Phariſees who were for tithing Mint, Aniſe and Cummin, and for divers waſhings, when they omitted and paſſed over the weightier matters of the Laws, <hi>Judgment, Mercy, and the Love of God; yea and made void the Commandments of God, that they might eſtabliſh their own traditions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By reaſon of theſe and other like pretenſions, they came at laſt to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration it ſelf, and withdrew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from Communion with the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox Chriſtians, as if they had not been Spiritual enough for their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion. <hi>They went out from us,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.19. <hi>Theſe are they who ſeparate themſelves, ſenſual, not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:66155:42"/>having the ſpirit,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Jude, ver.</hi> 19. And yet in this ſtate of Separation, they were ſo far from becoming a more pure and Spiritual Community, as that they were indeed the <hi>Synagogue of Satan,</hi> as they are ſtiled, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.9. as being moſt impure, both in prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple and practice; and were really <hi>Spots</hi> in the Chriſtian Feaſts of Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, before they ſeparated, <hi>Jude</hi> 12. And therefore it ſeems ſomewhat ſtrange that they ſhould fancy them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be more Spiritual than the Orthodox Chriſtians. But it ſeems they eſteemed themſelves more know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing than others in Evangelical Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and valued themſelves by that knowledge, and ſo came to arrogate to themſelves the Title of <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> or the <hi>Knowing men.</hi> For they to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile that which was indeed their corrupting the Chriſtian Religion with that Religion it ſelf, would needs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Chriſtian Doctrine in a more myſtical ſenſe than the Apoſtles &amp; Orthodox Chriſtians did. By which, and by wreſting the Scriptures of the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:66155:42"/>Old Teſtament to an undue ſence, they <hi>perverted the Goſpel of Chriſt,</hi> making it another thing, <hi>another Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel</hi> (as St. <hi>Paul</hi> phraſeth it) than it was in it ſelf, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.6. And by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of theſe Myſtical Speculations (which they eſteemed for Divine Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations) they conceited themſelves to have fellowſhip with God, even then, when in point of practice they walked in ways of darkneſs; as we may perceive by what S. <hi>John</hi> ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth concerning them, when he ſaith, <hi>If we ſay we have fellowſhip with him,</hi> God, <hi>and walk in darkneſs</hi> (as they did) <hi>we lie and do not the truth,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.6. Which plainly intimates, that they grounded this perſwaſion of their having fellowſhip with God, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſomewhat abſtracted from a good and holy life, (which is the proper end and uſe of Divine Knowledge, without which it will do them that have it no more good than it doth the Devils when they have it,) and what could that be but an opinion that their bare knowledge and belief
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:66155:43"/>of things, inveſted them with that priviledge? As too many in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner now a days hope to enjoy partner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or fellowſhip in the righteouſneſs of Chriſt, meerly upon account of their belief or Orthodox opinion, though of impure lives. And truly well might St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay in reference to theſe <hi>Gnoſticks,</hi> and in this very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect; <hi>if any man think that he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any thing</hi> (and values himſelf by that knowledge) <hi>he knoweth nothing yet as he ought to know,</hi> 1 Cor. 8.2. Theſe myſtical and unintelligible ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations, they called <hi>Science,</hi> though falſly, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith: and theſe they oppoſed to the plain and intelligible doctrine of the Apoſtles, (as the Quak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in like manner do theirs) in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of which, they erred from the faith, as we are told, in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.20, 21. —<hi>avoiding profane and vain bab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and oppoſitions of Science, falſly ſo called: which ſome profeſſing, have erred concerning the Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now when they had obtained a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation among ſimple people, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:66155:43"/>the Miniſters of Chriſt, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Chriſt, and of being for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and righteouſneſs, and more ſtrict and abſtmeious in ſome things than the true Apoſtles were, and more ſublime and ſpiritual: how eaſie a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was it then for them to mould the poor ſimple and deluded people into what form they pleaſed, eſpecially in things that tended to their eaſe in the fleſh?</p>
            <p>And no doubt but as they pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Apoſtolical Authority and to greater ſtrictneſs of life in ſome things, than they would acknowledge in the holy Apoſtles themſelves; So they would pretend likewiſe that ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyances with the Jewes on the one hand and with the gentiles on the other as they adviſed to and practiſed, did tend to the <hi>propagating</hi> of the Chriſtian Religion; and that by ſuch comply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances they might <hi>gain</hi> upon their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours and friends to come more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly over to them in the acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt and profeſſion of the Chriſtian Religion. And therefore,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:66155:44"/>as it ſeems, they taxed St. <hi>Paul</hi> with <hi>imprudence</hi> in preaching the Goſpel, and managing his Miniſtry in ſo blunt a manner as they thought he did, to the exaſperating of all ſorts againſt him. For St. <hi>Paul</hi> repreſented the thoughts that ſuch had of him, as had been corrupted by the falſe Apoſtles, when he ſaid; <hi>We are fools for Chriſts ſake, but ye are wiſe in Chriſt, i. e.</hi> in profeſſing Chriſt or the Goſpel of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8. They thought it ſeems that he had not been ſo prudent in managing the Chriſtian cauſe, as their new Teachers had taught them to be. For ſince they had met with thoſe wiſer methods, as they were taught to eſteem them to be, they had reign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Kings, free from thoſe di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances, oppoſitions and ſufferings, which <hi>Pauls</hi> way of profeſſing the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel had expoſed them to. And thus <hi>by good words and fair ſpeeches, they deceived the hearts of the ſimple, and cauſed diviſions and offences contrary to the doctrine they had once learned,</hi> Rom. 16.17, 18.</p>
            <pb n="65" facs="tcp:66155:44"/>
            <p>S. 13.3. When they had gained the reputation aforeſaid among the ſimple and carnal minded Profeſſors of the Goſpel, they could by virtue thereof eaſily incline them without any great ſcruple, to do any thing they would have them, to procure fair quarter from the Unbelievers among whom they lived. And therefore to give themſelves and their ſeduced ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents the greater liberty and eaſe in their minds to do ſuch things as they did in proſecution of their worldly deſign, without any great ſcruple, they broached among them the <hi>doctrine of licentiouſneſs</hi> under the notion of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty. They turned the grace of God into laſciviouſneſs,</hi> as S. <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>ver.</hi> 4. Of theſe and the courſe they took in this kind, St. <hi>Peter</hi> likewiſe ſpeaks thus, in 2 Pet. 2.19. <hi>While they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe them liberty, they themſelves are the ſervants of corruption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By theſe and other Scriptures it ſhould ſeem, they ſpread ſome ſuch Doctrine as this: That the Grace of God in Chriſt was ſo <hi>large,</hi> that if
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:66155:45"/>men did but believe in Chriſt, they were in no danger of damnation, though they uſed a greater liberty than ſuch as <hi>Paul</hi> would allow of. They thought it ſeems, that <hi>faith without works</hi> would have ſaved them: a conceit which St. <hi>James</hi> oppoſed them in, ſaying, <hi>What doth it profit my brethren, though a man ſay he hath faith and hath not works? can faith ſave him?</hi> Jam. 2.14. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives this character of thoſe falſe Teachers who did reſiſt the Truth preached by the Apoſtles, juſt as <hi>Jan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> withſtood <hi>Moſes, viz.</hi> that they <hi>were men of corrupt minds, reprobate, concerning the Faith,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.8. They held and taught corrupt notions concerning the doctrine of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſaved by Faith in Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And when once they perſwaded the people to believe ſuch a doctrine as tended to Liberty and Licentiouſneſs, and yet undertook to ſecure them of Salvation all the while, upon account of a notional Faith in Chriſt; what would they ſtick at, and what would
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:66155:45"/>they not do, under the notion of fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering and promoting the Chriſtian, the <hi>Catholick Cauſe,</hi> either to ſecure or procure their worldly enjoyments, and to gratifie their various luſts? Many when they perceived that by the doctrine of Faith in Chriſt, men were <hi>freed</hi> from the Law of <hi>Moſes,</hi> in many of thoſe things which before Faith came, the Jews were bound to obſerve, they were willing to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that this doctrine of the Faith of the Goſpel gave them a greater Latitude in other things alſo than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed it did. And this opinion as we may well ſuppoſe, occaſioned ſuch cautions as theſe: <hi>Brethren, ye have been called unto liberty, only uſe not li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty as an occaſion to the fleſh,</hi> Gal. 5.13. <hi>As free, and not uſing your liberty as a cloak of maliciouſneſs,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.16.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſome it ſeems went ſo far as to think they might do things in their own nature evil, ſo long as they did them for good ends; <hi>to ſin that grace might abound:</hi> and would have fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered this opinion on the Apoſtles
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:66155:46"/>alſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.8. <hi>As we be ſlanderouſly reported,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, and as ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that we ſay, let us do evil that good may come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From ſuch Libertine doctrines as theſe falſe Apoſtles broached under the notion of <hi>Evangelical priviledges;</hi> and to procure the more Converts to the Chriſtian profeſſion, ſprang, as it is very probable, thoſe curſed practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which turned to the reproach of Chriſtianity, and to the hindrance of its progreſs, of which we read in 2 <hi>Ep.</hi> of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and in the <hi>Ep.</hi> of <hi>Jude</hi> and other places.</p>
            <p>It's true they were not probably ſo bad at firſt as they were at laſt, but were led from one error to another, till they arrived at laſt to monſtrous heights of wickedneſs: as we have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſeen ſome in our days have done, who began but in Antinomianiſm at firſt; <hi>Evil men and ſeducers,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> (ſpeaking of thoſe falſe Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,) <hi>ſhall wax worſe and worſe, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving and being deceived,</hi> 2 Tim. 3.13. 2 Theſ. 2.10, 11.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:66155:46"/>
            <p>S. 14. Shall I now need after all that I have ſaid touching the deſign the falſe Apoſtles drove and the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how, to ſay any thing farther to unfold <hi>the working of the Myſtery of Iniquity</hi> in the Apoſtles daies? Seeing all upon the matter, which I have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto ſaid, tends, as I apprehend it, to ſhew what we are to underſtand by thoſe words of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in the 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>For the Myſtery of Iniquity doth already work.</hi> However take this far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther account briefly; In a Myſtery there is one thing hid under another: So that the inward and more ſecret part, is hardly diſcernable but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering men. So it was here in the buſineſs before us: The worldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the falſe Apoſtles and their corrupting the Chriſtian Religion to accompliſh it, were obſcured and hid under a ſhow and profeſſion of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity and Religious pretences, as that the Goſpel did <hi>allow</hi> of what they did, and <hi>ſtood in need</hi> of ſome things they did, to promote it.</p>
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:66155:47"/>
            <p>Before the Goſpel came, the Iniquity of the Gentiles, abominable Idolatries and groſs impurities both in worſhip and manners, was openly profeſt and practiſed. But when the Goſpel by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing among them had prevailed againſt theſe things, <hi>and had turned them from dumb Idols to ſerve the living God:</hi> Then <hi>Satan</hi> who, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>can transform himſelf into an Angel of Light,</hi> did by his miniſters labour to corrupt and <hi>entangle again, thoſe who were once clean eſcaped from them who lived in errour,</hi> the errour of Gentiliſm: but not ſo as to profeſs Gentiliſm a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, but under a <hi>ſhow</hi> of Chriſtianity to return to it in part. The Devil was too ſubtile to appear ſo openly as to tempt them to return to down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Gentiliſm again in the groſſeſt kind. For the Goſpel had come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them with ſuch demonſtration and power, by the ſigns and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and mighty deeds which did ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company it, and by that means had ſo triumpht over the Religion of the Gentiles, that the Devil could have lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:66155:47"/>hope of prevailing with them to return to downright Gentiliſm again, who had been but lately ſo convinced of the truth and excellency of the Chriſtian Religion, as to be brought to renounce Gentiliſm and to profeſs Chriſtianity. But he thought it beſt as the caſe ſtood, to go another way to work with them, and to put them upon corrupting the Chriſtian profeſſion by degrees, by mixing ſomething of Gentiliſm with it under the notion of being conſiſtent with it; yea as tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to promote it, by reconciling the heathen to it by meeting them half way. And that wherewith the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil, in temptations of this kind, bait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his hook, was by inſinuating that by this means they might keep fair quarter with their Infidel neighbours, render themſelves in ſome ſort friends to the world, ſtave off perſecution, and retain their worldly poſſeſſions, together with their Chriſtianity. This I apprehend to be the Myſtery of Iniquity of which the Apoſtle ſpeaks as then already working.</p>
            <pb n="72" facs="tcp:66155:48"/>
            <p>But when the Apoſtle ſaith, the Myſtery of Iniquity doth <hi>already work,</hi> referring to the time then <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent,</hi> he implies that the ſpreading and more eminent prevailing of it, was to be expected <hi>afterwards</hi> in time then to come: and to this agrees the ſcope of the place as well as the form of words and manner of ſpeaking there uſed. For when he ſaith, <hi>only he who now letteth, will let, untill he be taken out of the way;</hi> it's evident that the more general ſpreading and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing of this Myſtery, was for the preſent hindred, by that which in time would be removed, and that then it ſhould get up to its height. I will not undertake poſitively to determine who or what is meant by the <hi>he</hi> which the Apoſtle ſaith <hi>now letteth.</hi> But this I ſay, that if the falſe Apoſtles corrupting the Chriſtian Religion for worldly advantage, under pretence of that Religion, was not a Myſtery of Iniquity, and ſuch a Myſtery of Iniquity as was then working, then I confeſs I cannot imagine what was.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:66155:48"/>But if it were, then that which then hindred all ſuch as profeſt the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion (as the corrupt Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans did) from riſing to any conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able greatneſs in the world, muſt in all probability be it which did then lett or hinder that myſterious deſign managed under pretence of that profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from coming to that growth which afterwards it came to, when that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment was removed out of the way. And what did or could ſo much hinder ſuch as profeſt Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, from riſing to worldly greatneſs, as the then Roman power as <hi>Heathen?</hi> which was ſo far from preferring men for the Chriſtian profeſſion ſake, that it did depreſs and keep them under upon that very account. And if that were it which did lett (and you ſee what reaſon there is to think it was) Then the firſt Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> as Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh, and thoſe that ſucceeded him, (who when the Roman power as hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then was removed, and now become Chriſtian, did by advantage of that and by corrupt arts under religious
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:66155:49"/>pretences, riſe to that greatneſs in the world as to cauſe the world to wonder after them,) do fairly ſeem to be prophetically pointed at by the Apoſtle, as thoſe which ſhould car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry on the Myſtery of Iniquity to a greater height and prevalence, when that which hindred was taken out of the way, than it could reach to in the Apoſtles dayes.</p>
            <p>But I need not lay the ſtreſs of prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Authors of Popery to be the <hi>Actors</hi> of the <hi>ſecond part</hi> of the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Iniquity, upon this contexture of Scripture I have been beating up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: for the thing, I ſuppoſe, will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear evident enough of it ſelf, if there had been no ſuch thing written as what we have in 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. For if they out of a worldly deſign have corrupted the Chriſtian Religion un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of Religion as the falſe Apoſtles did, Then they muſt needs be found workers of Iniquity in a Myſtery as well as they. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they have or no, comes next to be enquired into: which brings me
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:66155:49"/>to the Second part of what I was to diſcourſe, and that is to <hi>juſtifie my comparing</hi> the Authors of Popery with the falſe Apoſtles, in managing a carnal and worldly deſign in corrupting the Chriſtian Religion under pretence of practiſing and promoting it.</p>
            <p>S. 15. To prepare my way to this, I ſhall premiſe for our better under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; that though the deſign and practice of the falſe Apoſtles and the Authors of Popery, agree in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral nature of them; yet they differ in ſome circumſtances. But then that wherein they do differ, does not tend to extenuate, but to aggravate the iniquity of the deſign of the Authors of Popery, and to render it more cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal than the ſame deſign was, whiles, and as it was managed by the falſe Apoſtles. The falſe Apoſtles acting their part in times of open oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt Chriſtianity, and of perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution for ſo much as but confeſſing the name of Chriſt, were under a ſore temptation of doing what they did at
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:66155:50"/>the firſt, only to ſave their lives, and to preſerve and get a livelihood in the World. Whereas thoſe that gave the firſt riſe to Popery, taking their turn in the world in Halcy on days and peaceable times, when perſecution for confeſſing Chriſt, was not only ceaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but them when the profeſſion of Chriſtianity was grown into honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable requeſt with High and Low, they were under no ſuch temptation of doing what they did in the way of their deſign, either to ſave their lives or livelihood, or to obtain an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable eſtate, becoming Biſhops of the Churches of Chriſt, being therein prevented by the bounty of Chriſtian Emperors. But their deſign and the m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ns uſed to effect it, was founded in an exceſſive thirſt and exorbitant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire after greatneſs and worldly domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation exceeding all bounds of modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And this difference renders the iniquity of the worldly deſign in the falſe Apoſtles, but little in compariſon of what it was in the Authors of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery. <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Men do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:66155:50"/>a thief, if he ſteal to ſatisfie his ſoul when he is hungry,</hi> Prov. 6.30. They pitty ſuch as through a kind of ſeeming neceſſity are drawn to do that which yet is no wiſe-juſtifiable under ſuch a Circumſtance, when the ſame thing done by another under no ſuch temptation, is looked upon with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation.</p>
            <p>To acquaint you then with the firſt <hi>riſe</hi> of Popery as founded in a world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſign, as at the firſt I acquainted you with the riſe of the falſe Apoſtles and their corrupting the Chriſtian Religion founded in a deſign for this world: I muſt firſt repreſent to you the ill uſe which ſome of the Biſhops made of that peace and proſperity which the Church of God at laſt came to enjoy, when the Emperors and Rulers of the world became Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans themſelves, and imployed their power and greatneſs to encourage and farther the profeſſion and practice of Chriſtianity. For when the Biſhops of the Churches came not only to be protected in the diſcharge of their
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:66155:51"/>Function by publick Authority, but alſo to be greatly honoured, and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly advanced for their Profeſſion and Function ſake; ſome of them were not able to ſtand under ſo great a weight of honour as was caſt upon them, without being puft up and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſported with Pride and Ambition. And this Pride and Ambition put them upon ſtriving and contending for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedency, preheminence, and ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority of Juriſdiction, which ſettled at laſt in a claim of <hi>Supremacy,</hi> made by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> in arrogating to himſelf the Title of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Biſhop,</hi> over all Biſhops and Churches in the world. And out of this pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed headſhip grew by degrees, the whole body of Popery, by which the Chriſtian Religion hath been corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>This exorbitant Power, claimed by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> could not be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held and maintained without the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance of ſuch other Biſhops and Presbyters as were willing to own and defend this headſhip. Nor could
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:66155:51"/>that be expected without their ſharing in the worldly advantages to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained thereby: Nor could that gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur which they deſigned for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, be maintained without a ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Revenue: Nor ſuch a Revenue be raiſed, had the plain, honeſt, and moderate methods of Chriſtianity been obſerved in it. For if thoſe me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods could have been obſerved, and their turn ſerved thereby, they would never have been at the trouble of inventing and defending new ones.</p>
            <p>That theſe ends deſigned therefore might be ſerved, certain <hi>additions</hi> to, and <hi>corruptions</hi> of the Scriptures and Chriſtian Religion, were pitcht upon as the likelieſt means to obtain them: but yet to be managed ſo, as that the people might be perſwaded that thoſe <hi>additions</hi> and <hi>corruptions</hi> were either <hi>parts</hi> of Chriſtian Religion, or neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary <hi>means</hi> to promote it. And theſe <hi>additions</hi> and <hi>corruptions</hi> are the things which we call <hi>Popery,</hi> and not any other things though held and
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:66155:52"/>done by Papiſts, which yet are agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Scriptures, and which other Chriſtians hold and do as well as they. I do not ſay, nor indeed think that the firſt Authors and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Popery, had in proſpect, or did practiſe all the additions and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions which afterward were found out by their ſucceſſors, as neceſſary to ſecure and uphold the Uſurped Power and Greatneſs. No more did their predeceſſors the falſe Apoſtles begin with all the evil devices which they were afterwards led to, to carry on their deſign.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now therefore come to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in ſome of thoſe <hi>additions,</hi> and to ſhew how they fall in with this worldly deſign projected by the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors of Popery, and how like they look to what was deſigned and done by the falſe Apoſtles. It may be eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of thoſe additions in difference between Proteſtants and Papiſts, may not directly tend to promote their worldly deſign, though many of them do <hi>remotely,</hi> which do not <hi>immediately:</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:66155:52"/>But yet that will afford them no relief though ſo it ſhould be: Becauſe when men invent ſome errors, for no other reaſon but becauſe they are ſervice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to them in their carnal and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt deſigns; it is not unuſual for God then to give up ſuch men to other abſurd opinions and practices, though not ſerviceable to them in any ſuch way. <hi>Becauſe they received not the love of the truth that they might be ſav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> (but the love of ſome errors, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead and under pretence of truth, that they might compaſs and bring about their worldly deſign) <hi>therefore,</hi> and for this cauſe, <hi>God ſhall ſend them ſtrong deluſions that they ſhould believe a lie, that they all might be damned who believed not the truth, but had pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>I intend not to diſpute the ſeveral points in difference between Papiſts and Proteſtants, or to prove them to be ſuch additions and corruptions as I term them to be: for that hath been done many a time over ſufficiently
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:66155:53"/>and abundantly already by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Authors. But methinks it ſhould go as far and ſignifie as much with the Popiſh <hi>Laity,</hi> if not much more, as a juſt and full confutation of thoſe additions as erroneous would do, when they ſhall come to ſee how they have been abuſed and impoſed upon by their <hi>Leaders</hi> and <hi>Guides,</hi> and made to believe and do ſuch things for the ſaving of their Souls, as have no ſuch tendency, but the contrary: and by dancing after their Pipe have been made uſe of as Engines, meerly to work their ends and to ſerve their carnal deſign by them: to ſqueez and drain them to fill themſelves: or as men make uſe of horſes to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry them out of the dirt and to eaſe themſelves by their labour. Which puts me in mind of the <hi>woman that ſate upon the Beaſt, having upon her forehead a name written, Myſtery Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon the great,</hi> &amp;c. Rev. 17.3.5. All that I would deſire of the <hi>Laity</hi> is, that they would ſee with their own eyes, and uſe their own reaſon in the
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:66155:53"/>things I ſhall now lay before them, and not ſuffer their <hi>Clergie</hi> to blow out the Candle, or to hoodwink them, while they play tricks and pick their pockets.</p>
            <p>In giving inſtances of the Popiſh corruptions, by which the deſign of domination and worldly greatneſs hath been begun and carried on by the Romiſh Biſhops and their Seconds and aſſiſtance, under a Religious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, I ſhall begin with that which was laid as the foundation of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal fabrick.</p>
            <p>S. 16. Firſt then they would bear the world in hand that the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> ſucceſſively, are St. <hi>Peter's</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, and as ſuch are inveſted with a kind of Apoſtolical Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and their See the Apoſtolical See; and that as St. <hi>Peter</hi> was ſuperiour to all Biſhops and Preſbyters in juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; ſo they, as his ſucceſſours, are ſo too: Yea, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> for the time being, is Chriſts Vicar on Earth, and viſible Head of the Church.</p>
            <pb n="84" facs="tcp:66155:54"/>
            <p>Which claim of theirs puts me in mind of thoſe who <hi>ſaid they were A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles but were not, but were found liars,</hi> Rev. 2.2. And if it ſhall be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed that the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> are ſucceſſours of theſe in their deſign and pretence; they themſelves have given a more cogent proof of it, than ever they did of being St. <hi>Peter's</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours in ſuch headſhip and power as they pretend to.</p>
            <p>But as the falſe Apoſtles by preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to be Apoſtles indeed, when they were nothing leſs, did procure to themſelves ſuch a reputation with thoſe that were deluded by them, as did greatly advantage them in that worldly deſign which they undiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernedly carried on under that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence; juſt ſo have the Popes, by mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their deluded adherents believe that they are St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſors, Chriſts Vicars and head of the Church, raiſed to themſelves ſuch a reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as is greatly advantagious to them alſo in the like but greater world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſign of theirs.</p>
            <pb n="85" facs="tcp:66155:54"/>
            <p>For as the Proſelytes of the falſe Apoſtles were by their deluſive per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion, made not only plyant, but even zealouſly active in ſerving them in their deſign; ſo have the deluded adherents of the Popes been in like manner, in ſerving them in theirs. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to what mould may not ſuch men caſt the people, when they have inſinuated themſelves into their opinion, to be ſuch marvellous men as they pretend themſelves to be? The <hi>Galatians</hi> though after the falſe Apoſtles had corrupted them, began to look upon <hi>Paul</hi> with a jealous eye, as if he had been their enemy, by expoſing them to that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in profeſſing the Goſpel, which the other taught them how to avoid: yet ſo long as they retained that venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for him which ſometime they had while they eſteemed him the undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Apoſtle of Chriſt; <hi>they could, if it had been poſſible, have pluckt out their very eyes to have given him,</hi> as he ſaith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.15, 16. And when the falſe Apoſtles were taken for true ones, they had ſuch an intereſt in the deluded people
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:66155:55"/>thereby, as that they did even what they would with them. Which made St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſay, <hi>ye ſuffer if a man bring you into Bondage, if a man devour you, if a man take of you, if a man exalt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> 2 Cor. 11.20. Words doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs applicable to the Popiſh <hi>Laity</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as great reaſon, as ever they were to the deluded <hi>Corinthians:</hi> So great is the power of falſe opinion, when men, whether falſe Apoſtles or Popes, are taken to be what they leaſt are.</p>
            <p>Beſides, as this lofty claim and high pretence of <hi>ſupremacy and headſhip</hi> over the whole Chriſtian world, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared the Popes way for commanding and doing what he pleaſed among them that received and owned him in that capacity: So it was the direct road to the higheſt pitch of Vain Glory; that is, of being eſteemed and honoured for what he is not; ſince all m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n are wont to proportion the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour they give to men, according to what they eſteem them to be. And honey is not ſweeter to the mouth,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:66155:55"/>than honour and glory is to ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous minds. And therefore if <hi>Diotre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phes loved to have the preheminence,</hi> and the falſe Apoſtles thought it a prize worth ſtriving for, to be counted the head of a ſmall party, when but low and kept under in the world; how was his Holineſſes fancy tickled, may we think, with the contemplation of being <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Head</hi> of the whole Chriſtian World! And what would not ambitious men give or do for ſuch a purchaſe, and to keep it when they have it? <hi>Simon Magus</hi> we know would have purchaſed the power of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miracles as the Apoſtles did, with money: but for what end? but that he might not be outdone by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and ſo loſe that high eſteem he had among the people whom he had deceived with his Magick, as if he had been <hi>the great power of God,</hi> even as the Popes have done by their Arts. I appeal to the Papiſts themſelves: is it not apparent that honour from men was a great part of the prize for which the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> ran, when
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:66155:56"/>he firſt laid his deſign for Univerſal Biſhop, and to bring all others under him? And hath it not been a ſweet morſel to his ſucceſſors for the time being, to be adored by the people as St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor, as Chriſts Vicar and viſible head of his Church, and to be ſaluted with the appellation of <hi>The moſt Holy Lord the Pope,</hi> and to have Kings do homage and kneel to them, yea, and to kiſs their very feet? That Pope underſtood well enough what he ſaid, when he ſaid, <hi>What need of the Net when the Fiſh is caught?</hi> Certainly this ſeeking and receiving honour from men at this rate by the Popes, hath been no very good argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to prove themſelves St. <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſors, who was ſo ſhie, as we know, of being worſhipped by <hi>Cornelius,</hi> and of receiving too much honour from men when he had wrought a Miracle indeed: for he ſaid, <hi>Ye men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>why marvel ye at this? or why look ye ſo earneſtly on us, as though we by our own power or holineſs had done this?</hi> Act. 3.12.</p>
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:66155:56"/>
            <p>Unity in Religion indeed hath been pretended as the reaſon of the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of ſuch an univerſal viſible Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> have claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: But <hi>unity</hi> of <hi>Conſent</hi> and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour in the people to <hi>honour</hi> them as ſuch, and to maintain them in that magnificence which hath followed that pretence and claim, hath doubtleſs been at the bottom when the other hath been at the top; as is viſible in the effects of it. If this were not ſo, they would never ſo patiently endure thoſe many differences and bitter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſts about Religion as they do, which are among the ſeveral Orders of men under their Government, provided they do but all agree in owning the Pope and his claim of Succeſſion, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, and Univerſal headſhip: Whereas let any but whiſper any thing againſt this, and he ſhall quickly find a watchful eye over him, and a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy hand upon him. So that 'tis <hi>ſelf-intereſt</hi> which is the White aimed at, that ſtill governs in the uſe of what power and preheminence is obtained,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:66155:57"/>though other things, to cover the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, are pretended.</p>
            <p>S. 17.2. Another of their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, is a pretence to an <hi>Inſallibility</hi> in the Popes, in their <hi>Decrees, Canons, Conſtitutions and Determinations,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from St. <hi>Peter,</hi> by virtue of their ſucceeding him. Not that it can be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably thought that they can in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt believe any ſuch thing concerning themſelves: For ſeveral things uttered and done by them, or ſome of them, have bewrayed their own miſgivings as to this, as I could ſhew: However they think fit to ſet a good face on't outwardly to the world, as being a thing neceſſary and uſeful for the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of their worldly deſign. For by perſwading the people to believe ſuch a thing concerning them, they get a great advantage to make them become perfectly their <hi>creatures.</hi> For if the people be made to believe that the Popes are Infallible and cannot err in the things aforeſaid, then they can have no pretence to diſpute any thing
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:66155:57"/>impoſed upon them by them, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their own belief, muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come perfectly Vaſſals, and yield ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute obedience to them: A thing, than which, what could be more cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly contrived by the Popes and their Confederates, to ſerve their ends upon the people?</p>
            <p>S. 18.3. And becauſe ſeveral Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Orders of men were thought as neceſſary to ſupport this Eccleſiaſtical Monarchy, as the <hi>Janizaries</hi> and <hi>Baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa's</hi> are to ſupport the <hi>Turkiſh;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome things likewiſe were thought neceſſary to procure <hi>reverence and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect</hi> to the Popes dependants in their ſeveral Orders and Degrees, to the end the people might ſtand the more in awe of them, and be the more ready to yield Obedience to them in execution of the ſeveral Offices and Orders they have received from the Pope their Head. One of which is a power of <hi>Abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Forgiveneſs</hi> of ſins, veſted in their Prieſts. Another is a power of making a God for the people to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:66155:58"/>by Tranſubſtantiating the Bread and Wine in the Sacrament, into the Real Body and Blood of Chriſt: And who would not be glad of the favour of ſuch wonderful men, and do any thing to pleaſe them? And by <hi>Auri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular confeſſion</hi> to a Prieſt, another of their corruptions, they lay the people under their mercy, being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by maſters of their Secrets, beſides the advantage of giving intelligence in ſpecial caſes, which muſt needs keep them in a continual awe of them. And by their receiving the Sacrament in both kinds, when the <hi>Laity</hi> are ſuffered to receive it but in one, (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother of their corruptions) a great and ſacred difference forſooth is put between the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laity.</hi> And beſides, the effect of the peoples pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Devotions, is made to depend upon the <hi>intention</hi> of the Prieſt, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther corruption; and therefore no need of having their Divine Service in the <hi>Vulgar tongue,</hi> another corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion likewiſe added to that: All ſtill tending to make the people the more
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:66155:58"/>
               <hi>dependant</hi> upon the Clergy, and the more <hi>governable</hi> by them in all things, while they live, and to be in the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter diſpoſition to be directed and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed upon by them in diſpoſing of a good part of their Eſtates to the uſe of the Church, when they die.</p>
            <p>S. 16.4. Although the Scripture ſaith, <hi>that every one ſhall bear his own burden, and give an account of himſelf to God:</hi> and tho' Chriſt hath ſaid <hi>Search the Scriptures,</hi> and the <hi>Bereans</hi> for doing ſo were highly commended; yet in contradiction hereto, the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Implicitie faith</hi> is ſet on foot; by which men are taught <hi>to believe as the Church believes, i. e.</hi> as their Prieſts believe, they believing what the Pope, or the Pope and a General Council of their own, have defined for matter of faith. And this alſo is one of their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions; and the <hi>forbidding the Laity to read the Scriptures without licence from their Biſhop,</hi> is another; and ſo is their Tenent that <hi>Ignorance is the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of devotion.</hi> And what is their end
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:66155:59"/>in theſe things? <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in the faith,</hi> and to <hi>keep people from running into hereſie,</hi> is pretended: (and is not put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out a mans own eyes that he may be led by another, a good expedient not to miſs his way?) but their end is to <hi>ſecure</hi> their corrupt principles and fraudulent arts from being <hi>inquir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> into by the people; and that the <hi>Laity</hi> may depend upon them as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Oracles, even in thoſe things which are impoſed upon them under one Religious pretence or other, when in truth it is but to ſerve the Pope and his Clergies intereſt, and to work their ends upon them undiſcovered. It is that the people might entirely and tamely reſign up themſelves to them, and be wholly at their diſpoſe in what they would have them believe and do, though otherwiſe it ſhould ſeem to them never ſo unreaſonable. And therefore <hi>Bellarmine (de Rom. pontif. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>fin.</hi>) was not aſhamed to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm, <hi>that if the Pope ſhould err in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding Virtues and commanding Vices, yet the Church were bound to believe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:66155:59"/>Vices to be good and Virtues bad, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſhe ſhould ſin againſt conſcience. But when the blind that are led and the blind that lead, are both in the ditch,</hi> it is not their ſaying they were led thither, will help them out.</p>
            <p>S. 20.5. Furthermore, although Chriſt upon occaſion of the two diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples deſiring of him that they might ſit the one on his right hand and the other on his left in that temporal King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom they fancied he was to have, ſaid to <hi>Peter</hi> and all the Apoſtles, <hi>Ye know that the Princes of the Gentiles exerciſe dominion over them, and they that are great exerciſe Authority upon them, but it ſhall not be ſo among you:</hi> I ſay, though this be ſo expreſs as you ſee, yet notwithſtanding the Pope as pretended ſucceſſour to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> claims a Supremacy <hi>over Kings,</hi> and a priviledge to be <hi>appealed to</hi> as the laſt and higheſt Tribunal upon earth. And in caſe any Kings turn hereticks to him in denying his Claim and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing off his yoke, he takes upon him
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:66155:60"/>a power to chaſtiſe them; to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate them, and then to depoſe and dethrone them, and to diſpoſe of their Kingdomes, and to abſolve their ſubjects from the duty of their allegiance to their natural Prince.</p>
            <p>And for what reaſon is this ſwell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power of overtopping Kings aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med? The pretence is, that the Pope as head of the Church being Superiour to all Chriſtian Kings, as being but members of that body whereof he is head, they upon that account are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his conduct and government in uſing their ſecular power for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt of the Chriſtian Religion and Catholick cauſe, and for the chaſtiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch as are heretical, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dutiful and diſobedient. This is the Pretence; But the true deſign is to render the Pope the more <hi>magnificent</hi> and <hi>venerable,</hi> the more <hi>awful and ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible</hi> in the eyes of all, and to <hi>lift</hi> him up to the <hi>higheſt</hi> pinnacle of worldly Pomp and greatneſs attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in this world, and to uſe the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and intereſt of ſuch Kings to <hi>ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port</hi>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:66155:60"/>and <hi>ſecure</hi> him in his Pontifical Chair of State, and as <hi>executioners</hi> of his wrath and diſpleaſure againſt all that ſhall but peep and mutter any thing againſt him, or any of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees or orders, or give him the leaſt diſturbance.</p>
            <p>That this is the deſign, tho' the other be pretended, appears in that the Pope is well enough contented that theſe Kings ſhould <hi>tolerate</hi> or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nive at any wickedneſs in their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, though never ſo diſhonour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Chriſt and Chriſtianity, and deſtructive to his Religion in the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of it, provided they be but tender of <hi>his</hi> Intereſt, and will not connive at any Affronts put upon his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as Papal. <hi>Men may do what they will, provided they meddle not with the Popes Crown or the Monks bellies,</hi> was the ſaying of <hi>Eraſmus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>S. 21.6 Again, as the Popes do claim a ſupremacy over Temporal Princes for <hi>themſelves,</hi> ſo they do a priviledge and <hi>exemption</hi> for their
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:66155:61"/>
               <hi>ſubordinate Clergie</hi> from the <hi>Temporal power;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Trid. Seſſ.</hi> 25.</note> as holding immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately under their Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Head, the Pope: which is another device to ſtrengthen their Intereſt. For hereby all his Clergy are the <hi>faſter tied</hi> and engaged to their grand Maſter the Pope, and at the greater liberty <hi>act</hi> ſecurely in abetting his Intereſt and ſerving his deſigns, as occaſion and opportunity ſerves.</p>
            <p>S. 22. 7. As the falſe Apoſtles broached Doctrines tending to Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſs, to increaſe their party and ſtrengthen their Intereſt: ſo the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors and Founders of Popery have ſet on foot certain corrupt <hi>doctrines,</hi> good for nothing but to <hi>increaſe their party</hi> and <hi>wealth</hi> thereby, and to <hi>ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> their Intereſt. Such is that of a pretended power veſted in the Pope, and from him derived to every Prieſt, of <hi>abſolving</hi> men and <hi>forgiving</hi> their ſins upon ſuch <hi>eaſie terms</hi> as the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing them to the Prieſt, and doing ſuch ſlight Penances, as he out of his
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:66155:61"/>Indulgence to them, if they pleaſe him, is pleaſed to appoint.</p>
            <p>And which is yet worſe, if worſe can be, <hi>viz.</hi> the Doctrine of the Popes power, not only of granting Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences for Sins paſt, but alſo Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations to commit them for time to come. And that ſuch a power is pretended to, we learn from Authors of their own. <hi>Eſpenſeus</hi> hath told us, that <hi>They</hi> allow not only the <hi>Laity,</hi> but alſo <hi>their very Clergie-men to dwell with Whores and Harlots, and to beget Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtards, for a certain Tax.</hi> Comment on Tit. p. 478, 479. <hi>Alſo,</hi> De Continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Lib. 2. Cap. 7. And <hi>the Princes of the Roman Empire aſſembled at</hi> Norem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg, <hi>in the years</hi> 1522, 1523. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained <hi>that the Popes ſucked the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of the peoples Eſtates by Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and that they heightened the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture by their hireling Cryers and Preachers, and that Chriſtian piety was baniſhed, while to advance their Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket, they cried up their Wares, for the granting of wonderful peremptory par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, not only of Sins already commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:66155:62"/>but of Sins that ſhall be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. So that by the Sale of theſe Wares, as they ſaid, together with being ſpoiled of their money Chriſtian Piety is extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed; while any one may promiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf impunity, upon paying the rate that is ſet upon the Sin he hath a mind to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit,</hi> Faſciculus rerum experendarum, <hi>fol.</hi> 177, 178. And if the people can believe that the Pope hath power by his Diſpenſations to bear them out for money in ſuch Immoralities, they may as well believe alſo that he hath power to diſpenſe with their taking of ſuch Oaths, and entering into ſuch Obligations which they never intend to keep, or to do any other thing as bad, eſpecially if it any way tend to the advancing of the Catholick Cauſe. And if ſo, by what <hi>Teſt</hi> can they be diſcovered to be really what they are, when they have a mind to conceal it? or what ſecurity can ſuch Oaths or other Obligations be to Proteſtant Princes, of their true alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance to them?</p>
            <p>And what is ſaid in this is the more
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:66155:62"/>conſiderable, it we add thereto thoſe other two looſe Doctrines of theirs, the one touching the lawfulneſs of their breaking Faith with Hereticks, ſuch as they eſteem Proteſtants to be, and the other the Jeſuitical Doctrine of Equivocation with mental Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves. Wherein alſo they exactly follow their Leaders, the <hi>falſe Apoſtles.</hi> For they, as I have ſhewed, thought, or at leaſt <hi>taught,</hi> that in ſome caſes they might deny Chriſt in word, ſo they did but retain a belief in him in their hearts; and partake with Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters in their Idol Sacrifices, ſo they did but retain in their minds a belief that there were no other Gods but one, and intended not any honour to the Idol.</p>
            <p>The very complexion of theſe, and ſuch like Doctrines, ſhews them to be calculated, not to promote Religion and Virtue, but to hook in filthy lucre, to gratifie any that will but be for them, in giving ſcope to their Luſts, and to ſet men free from all ties of Religion and Conſcience, when
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:66155:63"/>they ſtand in the way of their Cauſe and Intereſt. That which the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet of Old from the Lord charged upon the Prieſts, then when he ſaid, <hi>They eat up the ſin of my people, and ſet their heart on their Iniquity,</hi> Hoſ. 4 8. falls upon theſe men. For as thoſe were deſirous to have the people ſin that they might have the more Sin-offerings: So theſe are willing, we ſee, that the people ſhould have liberty allowed them to ſin, provided they will but buy the more Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Diſpenſations.</p>
            <p>And ſuch likewiſe is their doctrine of <hi>Aſſuring men of pardon</hi> when they are going out of the world, tho' they have lived never ſuch wicked and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious lives before, upon condition of <hi>Contrition and Confeſſion to a Prieſt:</hi> Yea upon condition of that Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and <hi>Attrition</hi> alone: which, as they define it, is <hi>a grief for ſin ariſing only from a fear of Hell.</hi> And I ſhould think no wicked man that believes or fears that there is a Hell, can lightly be without ſuch a ſorrow at laſt. And
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:66155:63"/>if men could be made to believe or hope that they may keep their ſins and yet be pardoned, at leaſt upon ſuch eaſie terms as we ſee they are taught to believe they may, it would then be matter of wonder that there is no more, rather than that there are ſo many Papiſts in the world.</p>
            <p>Such doctrine as this is, doubtleſs, the reaſon, why now and then ſome profligate perſons, and ſo many Thieves and Murderers, when condemned to die, turn Papiſts, that were no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than practical Atheiſts before.</p>
            <p>S. 23.8. And yet leſt their looſe principles and practices ſhould render them too much ſuſpected for Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, they, juſt as the <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, would <hi>ſeem</hi> to be even more devout in ſome things than the purer Chriſtians that oppoſe them in their carnal deſigns. And therefore they have impoſed upon themſelves and their Votaries certain things, as parts of Religion, which God hath not made ſo, and are more careful to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:66155:64"/>them, than what God hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded; as the Phariſees before them were, in reference to their traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Such is their abſtaining from ſome ſorts of meats upon ſuch and ſuch dayes; not upon a <hi>Civil</hi> account, which may lawfully be done, but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>Religious</hi> account. And it's well if, at leaſt, many of them do not make more conſcience of eating fleſh on a <hi>Fryday</hi> than to ſwear or lie. The exerciſing certain ſeverities up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their own bodies at certain ſet times of the year by way of Penance: the reſtraining thoſe that are in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Orders from Marriage: the Vows of Poverty and Single life, are alſo things of like nature with thoſe which the falſe Teachers in the Apoſtles times impoſed upon their Proſelytes, as I have ſhewed. And ſo was the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping of Angels, a thing which theſe Popiſh Chriſtians alſo teach. Nay they pretend to make ſhow of ſuch great love to Chriſt more than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers do, as that for his ſake they worſhip ſuch as are related to him,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:66155:64"/>as the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> and other Saints: And not only ſo, but to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip his very Picture, and to have in ſacred eſteem the very Reliques of his ſervants, or thoſe which they eſteem to be ſo: Like the Phariſees of old, who <hi>builded the Tombs of the dead Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and garniſhed the Sepulchres of the Righteous</hi> that were dead; when at the ſame time they perſecuted thoſe that were living, as theſe alſo have done.</p>
            <p>By ſuch arts as theſe they have made a covering, ſuch as it is, for their Irreligious deſigns, by which they have deluded people of groſs minds that are influenced by ſenſe in the way of Religious worſhip, as Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious and Idolatrous perſons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes have been, but have miſappre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of the Nature of God, and of that Spiritual worſhip which is agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to his Nature and acceptable to him. Which alſo makes them think that the eating of Chriſt's Fleſh and the drinking of his Blood in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament in a natural and proper ſence, is that which is available: like the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:66155:65"/>
               <hi>Capernaumites,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>how can this man give us his Fleſh to eat?</hi> under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding him in a groſs ſence, when he had ſaid to them, <hi>The bread that I will give is my fleſh, which I will give for the life of the world: And except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his blood, ye have no life in you,</hi> Joh. 6.</p>
            <p>Moreover, to raiſe yet the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter opinion in the people of the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their way, they ingroſs the whole of true Chriſtianity to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſtiling thoſe and thoſe only of their way, the <hi>Catholique Church;</hi> denying Salvation to belong to thoſe that are not of it, accounting them Hereticks. Herein likewiſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the guiſe of the falſe Apoſtles and their Diſciples, who laboured to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſs to themſelves the name and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of the moſt Knowing and moſt Spiritual, ſeparating from the reſt of Chriſtians, as if they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves only had been the true Church, thereby to put the better colour upon their corrupting the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:66155:65"/>and the worldly end for which they did it.</p>
            <p>S. 24.9. And then to fill the Churches treaſuries, and to draw to themſelves the wealth of the world, and thereby to ſupport all their glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and grandeur, and to glut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with ſenſual pleaſures and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights, they have uſed other methods and Arts alſo. One of which is the doctrine of the <hi>Merit</hi> of good works; For when the people are made to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that they may by good works, Almſdeeds, and Donations to pious uſes, make <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> to God, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure <hi>exemption</hi> from Purgatory, and <hi>merit</hi> Heaven; and by abounding in them may <hi>ſupererogate;</hi> and not only merit enough for themſelves, but have to ſpare for others; Then it is no hard matter to perſuade them to be very liberal and kind to their Ghoſtly Fathers while they live, being to them in Gods ſtead to pardon them, and to leave a conſiderable part of their eſtates to the Church, when they die.</p>
            <pb n="108" facs="tcp:66155:66"/>
            <p>The forbidding Marriage to the Clergy ſerves to the ſame end alſo; which may be one reaſon of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraint. For when they, eſpecially thoſe of the higher degree that have great Eſtates, can leave no Children lawfully begotten to inherit; who is likelier to be their Heir than the Church? eſpecially conſidering that the Canon Law allows not Regular Biſhops to diſpoſe of their Eſtates by Will.</p>
            <p>Another device to get money, is the <hi>Tax of the Apoſtolick-Chancery;</hi> a grant by ſeveral Popes of Pardons, at ſuch and ſuch a price for thouſands of years, though their ſins be of a deep die. It is true, there are, I muſt needs ſay, very good peniworths to be had, if the Ware be not counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit: One may have that for 18 Pence, 2 Shillings, or half a Crown, that a man would give all he is worth for, be it never ſo much, were he ſure he ſhould not be cheated in his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe. But as for all thoſe that have faith enough to believe the Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:66155:66"/>of the Popes, in aſſuring them of Pardons at ſuch <hi>cheap</hi> rates, (and if they queſtion it in this, they may queſtion it in all the reſt,) methinks there ſhould not one of them fail to buy one of theſe Pardons that can go to the price of them: and who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not? And if ſo, who can count the vaſt ſums of money which we may rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably conceive this device will bring into the Popes Exchequer from age to age?</p>
            <p>Another Engine for the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, is <hi>Shrine Oblations:</hi> that is, the Offerings which the people make when they go on Pilgrimage to viſit the Shrine of ſuch or ſuch a Saint, whether voluntarily, or in a way of Penance. And the Treaſuries of the Shrines of ſome eminent Saints, are upon this account ſo rich, as that it's ſaid they may vie it with the Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Great Princes.</p>
            <p>Another Screw is, <hi>Commutation of Penances;</hi> that is, the buying off the doing of ſuch or ſuch Penance, for ſo much money as the Confeſſor or
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:66155:67"/>Ghoſtly Father ſhall be pleaſed to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them for: and he knows well enough how to put the price accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ability of the purchaſer; and ſo he doth alſo how to make the Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance greater or leſſer as he pleaſes. And this falls out ſo often, and with ſo many in all Popiſh Countries, that the Income thereby muſt needs be very great, beſides the ordinary Tithes they receive.</p>
            <p>The fictious <hi>doctrine of Purgatory,</hi> to name no more, is, I aſſure my ſelf, none of the leaſt of the Artifices of the Founders of Popery, to accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulate a prodigious maſs of wealth: of which Doctrine and device, take this brief account. Firſt, The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are made to believe, that though God pardons Mortal Sins to the truly penitent, ſo as to free them from Eternal Torments; Yet ſince they have much Venial Sin and Corruption, in which oft-times they die, not hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made ſufficient ſatisfaction by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances enjoyned them here, they muſt expiate theſe, and ſatisfie for them,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:66155:67"/>by ſuffering the pains of Purgatory. And farther, they muſt believe alſo, that the Church hath a Treaſure or <hi>ſtock of Merits</hi> ariſing out of Works of Supererogation done by ſuch as have merited more than enough for themſelves, the <hi>over-plus</hi> ſtill running into the <hi>common ſtock:</hi> and that the Pope, and Prieſts from him, have the power of <hi>diſpoſing and applying</hi> theſe out of the common ſtock to particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar perſons that need them. And far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they are taught to believe that this Treaſure of the Church is not drawn out and diſtributed but by <hi>Indulgences:</hi> and that ſince theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences are for the <hi>relief</hi> of the Churches <hi>Indigences,</hi> they are not to be obtained without being <hi>purchaſed.</hi> Now when the poor deluded people are made to believe all theſe idle Ficti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for real Truths, and come to have their Conſciences awakened on their Death-beds; what will they not give to obtain theſe Indulgences, and for Maſſes to be ſaid, and Prayers to be made, that they may be delivered from
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:66155:68"/>Purgatory, a place of Torment little leſs than Hell. Skin for skin and all that a man hath, will he give for his Life; how much more for his <hi>Soul!</hi> So that the fruit and effect of this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as we may well conceive, is no ſmall or inconſiderable thing. And therefore it was no leſs truly than wittily ſaid, <hi>The fire of Purgatory keeps the Popes Kitchin warm, and makes his Pot to boyl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall inſtance in no more: but theſe I have named are ſome of the Arts, and part of the Craft in the Myſtery of Iniquity, by which, <hi>Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trius</hi> like, <hi>they get their wealth.</hi> And truly ſo vaſtly great hath been the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Income of the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> from all Nations of their Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that according to the account giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en from amongſt themſelves, by <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew Paris</hi> for one, (<hi>M. Par. Hist. An.</hi> 1252.) its yearly Revenue from <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> alone, by one way and another, more than I have named, amounted to no leſs heretofore, than twice ſo much as the then Kings Revenue.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:66155:68"/>
               <q>No marvel then if the Biſhops of <hi>Rome,</hi> and their Cardinals, former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poor Prieſts and Deacons, are now become Illuſtrious, and for Pomp and Magnificence, able to vie it with great Princes, and to raiſe their Families, Nephews and Nie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to Dignities and Fortunes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great, as is well known to the World.</q>
            </p>
            <p>S. 25. And now I having made this Compariſon between the <hi>ſalſe Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Founders of Popery</hi> in their world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſign and curſed means of accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhing it; all that I ſhall deſire of the <hi>Lay</hi> Catholicks, as they call them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, is, that they would but beſtow ſo much <hi>conſideration</hi> upon what is here offered, as by which they may come to make an impartial judgment whether or no I have wronged the latter by comparing them to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. And if I have not, as I doubt not but they will find I have not, if prejudice and prepoſſeſſion do not make them err in judgment, as too
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:66155:69"/>frequently it is wont to do; Then methinks I ſhould not need to uſe one word to perſuade them to deſiſt from following their guides any longer blindfold by an implicite faith; for their own Intereſt both ſpiritual and temporal, which uſeth to be moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent with men, will prompt them to this. Can they poſſibly think it ſafe for them to commit themſelves to the conduct of thoſe, who directly follow the track, and tread in the ſteps of the <hi>falſe Apoſtles,</hi> who for ſelf ends and worldly advantage, Avarice and Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, betrayed the Religion of the holy Jeſus, and the Souls of men? <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes, <hi>In vain is the net ſpread in the ſight of any bird.</hi> And will they be more ſilly than the fowles of the Air, in not endeavouring to make their eſcape when the <hi>Snare</hi> is diſcovered to them? <hi>Remember this and ſhew your ſelves men,</hi> may be ſaid to them, as once it was by the Prophet to others.</p>
            <p>But we know the manner of theſe mens <hi>Guides;</hi> either they will not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:66155:69"/>them to read diſcourſes which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect their fraud: or if they happen to hear or ſee any thing of that nature, they can, as they would have them think, blow off all with one blaſt of their mouth. I do therefore heartily wiſh that the <hi>Laicks</hi> I ſpeak of, would at laſt be ſo wiſe for their ſouls as to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, That when their <hi>Clergie,</hi> whom they follow by an Implicite faith, do make their defence againſt us in what we charge them with, they are then <hi>concerned</hi> in point of a Carnal ſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt: and where that rules and is predominant, it ſtill obliges men to put the faireſt colour they poſſibly can upon their Cauſe, though never ſo bad, <hi>without</hi> regard to truth; <hi>that</hi> not being the thing they ſtrive for, but their <hi>ſelfiſh intereſt.</hi> And it is the manner of ſuch men, when they have done ſo, to glory over their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries from the teeth outward, as if they had laid them dead at their feet: When at the ſame time inwardly they feel themſelves ſtruck to the very heart by the clear evidence and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſiſtable
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:66155:70"/>force of their Adverſaries rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonings. And the reaſon of their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo is, becauſe they find that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they can preſerve their intereſt among the people that have given up themſelves to them, and pinn'd their faith upon their ſleeves; this courſe of theirs ſerving their end as ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually as a real confutation would do.</p>
            <p>And herein alſo they as evidently follow the ſteps of the <hi>falſe Apoſtles,</hi> as in any of thoſe other things I have inſtanced in. For although they, the <hi>falſe Apoſtles,</hi> could not ſtand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the powerful conviction of the faithful Apoſtles, but found their hearts to ſink within them, as to the Cauſe they maintained, as knowing in their conſciences they were not able by the ſtrength of truth to defend it againſt the aſſaults of the holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: yet then they would in face and outward appearance, glory and boaſt, as if they had the victory, and all becauſe they had no other way to hold their party to them and to carry
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:66155:70"/>on their deſign, which they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to ſtick to, whatever was ſaid againſt it: and alſo becauſe they found that this courſe of theirs would do them as much ſervice as a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion would do among their credulous followers, who hung upon their lips, and were willing to take all they ſaid upon <hi>truſt,</hi> as ſuiting moſt with what they liked beſt. See for this the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. <hi>We commend not our ſelves again unto you,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, but give you occaſion to glory on our behalf, that you may have ſomewhat to anſwer them which glory in appearance, and not in heart:</hi> meaning the falſe Apoſtles,</p>
            <p>All that I ſhall add is only to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve from what was laſt delivered, That the <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> even then when they ſet the beſt face upon their Cauſe, and gloried over their oppoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and carried it outwardly with never ſo great confidence and boaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; yet ſince their own corrupt <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> was concerned in the <hi>Conteſt,</hi> there was juſt cauſe for their follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to ſuſpect what they pleaded in
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:66155:71"/>their own defence, and that it was wiſdome in them that did ſo, and folly and unhappineſs in thoſe that ſuffered themſelves to be impoſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and deluded thereby, without looking more narrowly into the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter themſelves, as thoſe did who <hi>try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them that ſaid they were Apoſtles but were not, and found them liars,</hi> Rev. 2.2. And if ſo; then in as much as a Corrupt ſelf intereſt of Popiſh Guides is alſo concerned in and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the cauſe they labour to defend, as I have ſhewed; thoſe who have committed themſelves to their Conduct, have no more reaſon to be confident of the goodneſs of their Cauſe upon the account of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and boaſting of thoſe who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake to defend it, than the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of the falſe Apoſtles had in reference to <hi>their</hi> cauſe: But in point of greateſt prudence are concerned to look upon all they ſay with a jealous eye, and with the greateſt care and diligence to ſcan the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter themſelves, and to ſearch the
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:66155:71"/>Scriptures themſelves, and imparti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to conſider as well what is ſaid againſt them and their Cauſe, as what is ſaid for it and them, and not careleſly or deſperately to <hi>venture</hi> their ſouls upon ſuch mens confident pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, whoſe Corrupt <hi>intereſt</hi> it is to <hi>deceive</hi> them.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:66155:72"/>
            <pb n="121" facs="tcp:66155:72"/>
            <head>APPENDIX.</head>
            <p>WHat you ſhall find in this Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendix was firſt intended to be brought in by way of Digreſſion at the cloſe of the Anſwer to an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Compliances, at the end of the 9th. Section of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Diſcourſe, to which it proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly relates. But its running out to ſuch a length as it hath done, hath altered that intention, as tending to too great an interruption in the line and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of that Diſcourſe. And I have the rather thought it meet to add this to the whole Diſcourſe, leſt any ſhould think a compliance in the uſe of ſome undetermined circumſtances in the adminiſtration of Gods Publick Worſhip, ſhould be of like nature with the corrupt compliances of the
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:66155:73"/>
               <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> and their party, diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſaid Diſcourſe. That which I have to add therefore upon the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid occaſion, take as follows.</p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid in the foreſaid Section touching St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Compliances, ſomewhat may be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed which may be of good uſe to Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in many dubious Caſes. There I have ſhewed how that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times withſtood the uſe of Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſometimes yielded to it.</p>
            <p>The reaſon of which did ariſe from the different circumſtances that did attend the uſe of the ſame thing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on different occaſions. When it was urged upon the Gentiles as neceſſary to their ſalvation, St. <hi>Paul</hi> withſtood it: But to avoid ſtumbling in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Jews, who were not as yet ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied touching its ceſſation, and to prevent a breach in the Church, and to gain the more upon ſuch as were inclinable to Chriſtianity, he yielded to the uſe of that and other like things among them.</p>
            <p>I think we may ſafely ſuppoſe that
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:66155:73"/>St. <hi>Paul</hi> knew well enough when he did ſo, that Circumciſion was not in it ſelf, or by poſitive command neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to the Jews under the Goſpel, by the taking place of which it was aboliſhed; for he ſaid, <hi>Circumciſion is nothing,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.19. Nor was it ſimply unlawful in it ſelf; for if it had, no Circumſtance could have ſanctified it or made it lawful. So that when he yielded to it, it was upon account of <hi>Expediency</hi> by reaſon of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances attending it, which made it expedient; ſuch as was the Peace of the Church, and the better propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Goſpel. And yet when he yielded to it upon the account of Expediency, we may well ſuppoſe it was not wholly and altogether expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient without any inexpediency at all, but only <hi>more</hi> expedient than in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expedient. For otherwiſe it may well be thought, that his yielding to the uſe of it ſomewhat tended to nouriſh the opinion the <hi>Jews</hi> had of its perpetuity under the Goſpel, and to miniſter ſome advantage to thoſe who taught a
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:66155:74"/>neceſſity of it unto Salvation, and could not be very grateful to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Gentiles who oppoſed it, nor to St. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf neither. So that in ſome reſpect it was inexpedient to yield to it when he did yield to it, but in other reſpects <hi>more</hi> inexpedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to withſtand it and not to yield to it.</p>
            <p>From all which we may obſerve, that when two Inexpediencies come in competition, the one attending the doing, and the other the not doing of the ſame thing, ſo that there is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity to yield to one of them in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or not doing of it, then that which is <hi>leaſt</hi> inexpedient, is to be yielded to. Or which is the ſame; that when all circumſtances are conſidered, then that which hath <hi>more</hi> of expediency than inexpediency in it, is to be choſen. Juſt as on the other hand, when two Precepts, the one moral, the other but poſitive, come in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petition, the leſs is to give place to the greater.</p>
            <p>To fit theſe general Rules to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:66155:74"/>caſes requires ſome skill: but if theſe things were well conſidered and practiſed, it would go a great way towards the leſſening thoſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due diſtances which are among us. As for inſtance: Suppoſe ſome cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances in the external form of our Publick Worſhip, eſtabliſht by Law, were ſo <hi>inexpedient</hi> as ſome deem them to be; Yet if they would but lay aſide Prejudice, Partiality, Paſſion, and Intereſt of Parties in making a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of things, by what hath been fairly argued from Scripture by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, to ſatifie doubtful minds concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, I am very confident they might eaſily come to plenary ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in their own minds touching this one thing, <hi>viz.</hi> That to <hi>bear</hi> with thoſe things for the peace of the Church, and the Intereſt of Religion in general, <hi>is not ſo inexpedient</hi> as it is by dividing the Church, by forſaking that Worſhip, to <hi>expoſe</hi> our Religion to the ſcorn and contempt of Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts, Infidels, and Papiſts, and to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, alas, too many others to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:66155:75"/>ſuch: and as it is, to confound and unſettle the minds of well mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but injudicious people, and to betray them into the hands of ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers: and as it is to divert mens minds from the ſerious conſideration, ſtudy, and practice of the weightier matters of Religion, and to engage them in contentious janglings, and uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble revilings and cenſurings, to the deſtruction of true Piety, and placing Religion much in Opinion, and in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a different form and party: and laſtly, as it is, to expoſe us all to the danger of the breaking in of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, by ſtrengthning their hands who are of that way, and by weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning our own, and by encouraging them in hopes of ſucceſs by our Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, to practiſe upon us, and by all their Arts to improve the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage we put into their hands by our diſtractions: and yet theſe, and ſuch like, have been the effects of dividing our Church.</p>
            <p>And if to <hi>bear</hi> with thoſe external circumſtances of Worſhip, for the ſake
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:66155:75"/>of the peace and edification of the Church and ſecuring to us our Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, be not <hi>ſo</hi> inexpedient, as it is to <hi>draw</hi> on us the foreſaid bad effects of our di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>viſions by withdrawing from the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip it ſelf, for the ſake of thoſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances; Then the Rule before laid down, and according to which St. <hi>Paul</hi> acted, ſhews which of theſe <hi>inexpediencies</hi> (in caſe both ſhould be ſuch) is to be yielded to, and born with, that the other may be avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Now that to <hi>bear</hi> with the foreſaid Circumſtances of worſhip, is not ſo inexpedient, as it is to cauſe diviſions and the Conſequents of them by forſak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the worſhip for their ſake, will eaſily appear by this, <hi>viz.</hi> In that the Lord hath not declared himſelf againſt the former, as he hath done againſt the latter. Although God hath expreſly appointed the ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial parts of his worſhip, as the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the Word, Prayer, and Sacraments, yet he hath not ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly appointed the external form,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:66155:76"/>method, manner and circumſtances of Adminiſtration, as whether it ſhall or ſhall not be adminiſtred according to the external circumſtances required in our Liturgy; but hath left things of that nature to be ordered by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral rules of Education, Comelineſs, and Order, according to the beſt ſkill and prudence they have, into whoſe hands the providence of God hath put the ordering of affairs of that nature. And although the external form of adminiſtration of Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip may be comparatively <hi>better</hi> in one Nation or Church than in another (when but all one in <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi>) as it would be in particular congregations alſo, if all Miniſters were left to their own liberty therein; Yet the <hi>meaneſt</hi> of them would not be <hi>unlawful,</hi> ſo long as nothing is done in <hi>oppoſition</hi> to any divine precept, or to the <hi>defeating</hi> of the end of the external adminiſtration of Gods pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick worſhip. But God hath not left men to any ſuch latitude to cauſe or not to cauſe diviſions and offences in
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:66155:76"/>the Church, as he hath for them to uſe different forms and circumſtances of forms in his publick worſhip: and therefore there cannot be the like rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to pretend Inexpediency in ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to them, as there is in cauſing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and offences in the Church by forſaking the publick worſhip up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on account of them. If the honour of God and good of men had been as much concerned in the external form of his worſhip, in not having it in this way but in that, as they are in mens keeping the <hi>unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace,</hi> we have all reaſon on our ſide to think he would then have been as particular and expreſs for this form and againſt that, as he hath been for the peace, unity, and charity of the Church, and againſt their contraries and their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary effects, which yet he hath not been.</p>
            <p>What God ſaid to the <hi>Jews,</hi> when he found them hot for Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, but cold and careleſs in the
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:66155:77"/>
               <hi>moral</hi> part of Religion, may with a little variation be very aptly applyed to our caſe in hand. <hi>I ſpake not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Fathers nor commanded them in the day that I brought them out of the Land of Egypt, concerning burnt Offerings or Sacrifices. But this thing commanded I them, ſaying, obey my Voice, &amp;c. but they hearkened not,</hi> &amp;c. Jer. 7.22, 23, 24. For when our Lord Chriſt ſees us more nice about forms of worſhip, and more zealous for this and againſt that, than we are for peace and Charity, and the honour and ſafety of our Religion and the good of other mens ſouls, which are greatly wronged and endangered by our diviſions, may he not as truly ſay, <hi>When I gave forth the Goſpel, ſpake I a word to my Diſciples to be hot for that external form of worſhip you contend for in oppoſition to that you contend againſt? But this I ſaid, have Salt in your ſelves and peace one with another: let all your things be done in Charity, endeavouring to keep the
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:66155:77"/>unity of the Spirit in the bond of peace: that no man put a ſtumbling block or an occaſion to fall in his brothers way, that none occaſion be given to the adverſary to ſpeak reproachfully;</hi> and wo to the world becauſe <hi>of offences, and wo to him by whom the offence cometh: and yet you have not been curious, nice and cautious in theſe as you have been about the other.</hi> Which if true, what account can be given for our breaking the Church in pieces and expoſing our Selves, our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and the Spiritual and eternal concerns of others, to ſuch damage, perils and hazards as have been mentioned, and all for the ſake of that which he commanded not? I ſay commanded not, <hi>definitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For doubtleſs they have been un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a very great miſtake who have aſſerted that nothing is to be done in the worſhip of God which he hath not commanded, if they mean it not only of the intrinſick matter and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:66155:78"/>of his worſhip, but alſo of all external circumſtances of adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as appears, I ſuppoſe, by what I have already ſaid, and by a due conſideration of thoſe very Scriptures upon which that opinion is ſuppoſed to be founded. Such as <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.3. <hi>Jer.</hi> 7.31. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.5. <hi>&amp;</hi> 32.35. <hi>Levit.</hi> 10.1. compared with <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.12. <hi>&amp; Chap.</hi> 6.12, 13. Where when ſome have been cenſured by God for doing what he commanded them not, it was in reference to falſe worſhip in the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> of it, done in oppoſition to what he had otherwiſe expreſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed and commanded, but never in reference to undetermined Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the adminiſtration of the true worſhip. And therefore theſe Scriptures when duly conſidered, are without any colour of reaſon or truth alledged againſt the lawful uſe of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>determined Circumſtances of admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Subſtance of Gods worſhip. An opinion doubtleſs it is no leſs dangerous than falſe. For
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:66155:78"/>ſince it cannot be conceived (as I ſuppoſe) how the publick worſhip other than the uſe of the Lords pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the reading the Scriptures, and the reciting ſome words of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in the adminiſtration of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm and the Lords Supper, (if ſo much) can poſſibly be managed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doing ſomething therein in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to external adminiſtration, which is not particularly determined and commanded in the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſuch a poſition as that muſt needs tend not only to fill mens minds with endleſs ſcruples, and their mouths with endleſs diſputes, but alſo to interrupt and put a ſtop to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Gods publick wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ſhould it be admitted.</p>
            <p>Even under the <hi>Moſaical</hi> diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when things pertaining to the worſhip of God were far more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutely determined than they are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, many things were done of a religious nature, and ſome of them more immediately reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:66155:79"/>the worſhip of God, which yet were neither commanded by God, nor the doing of them cenſured by him, ſo far as appears, ſo long as any thing Commanded by him was thereby neither oppoſed nor juſtled out, nor any thing done in the name or under pretence of things appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him, which were not ſo, as the Phariſees did, when <hi>they taught for doctrine the commandments of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of things of this nature, theſe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing are inſtances. The rearing of an <hi>Altar</hi> by the two Tribes and half, for a ſign or <hi>witneſs</hi> that they and their poſterity were people of the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to prevent Apoſtaſie in their poſterity, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 22.25.34. The erecting of a ſtone by <hi>Joſhua</hi> for ſomewhat a like purpoſe, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.26, 27. <hi>Solomons</hi> hallowing the middle part of the temple for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.64. The keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Paſſeover <hi>fourteen dayes,</hi> by order of <hi>King Hezekiah</hi> and with
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:66155:79"/>the advice of the Heads of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, tho' God had appointed but <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> as alſo the Levites then help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Prieſt in the Prieſts appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate work, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 30. The ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the dayes of Purim: The anniverſary faſts of the 4th. 5th. 7th. and 10th. month: The building of Synagogues for publick worſhip, and appointing governours therein, and the ordering what pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhould be made, and how and after what manner the Law and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets ſhould be improved to common benefit by reading and exhortation, and what diſcipline ſhould be uſed therein: The determinate hours of prayer in the Temple, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.1. The altering the geſture and ſome other things, in eating the Paſſeover, from what was uſed in the firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and conformed to by Chriſt himſelf under that alteration: The ſeaſt of Dedication, which Chriſt graced with his own preſence: The admitting of Proſelytes by Baptiſm
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:66155:80"/>as wel las by Circumciſion: a practice which our Saviour was ſo far from teſtifying his diſlike of as a humane invention, that he choſe the ſame rite by which to initiate his diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</p>
            <p>Theſe things, with what was ſaid before, if there were no more to be ſaid in the caſe, would be enough to ſhew that it's no juſt exception a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our external form of publick worſhip, in that it is not expreſly and particularly commanded in Scripture; for if it were, it would be a juſt exception againſt every external form of publick worſhip whatſoever; becauſe there is no one in particular commanded with excluſion of all the reſt. Which ſtill plainly renders it a thing more inexpedient, (yea and much more than ſo) to be <hi>acceſſary</hi> by rending from the communion of the Church, to the bringing on us all thoſe ſad effects of our diviſions, which every good man is ſenſible of, than it is or can be to <hi>bear</hi> with what
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:66155:80"/>does not ſo well pleaſe them in our form of worſhip as ſomewhat elſe different therefrom would do.</p>
            <p>Methinks it ſhould make ſuch as are more conſidering men among thoſe that divide the Church by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing from her communion, to be very <hi>jealous</hi> of the expediency of their practice, when they conſider that before men took this liberty, there was little of the ſad effects fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned viſible among us, but ſince that, thoſe bad effects are grown notorious and formidable; and that's no honour to Separation that it hath brought forth ſuch fruit: they may know what it is by what it hath done, <hi>by its fruits ye ſhall know it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And therefore ſuch as would be loth to lye under the guilt, unrepent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of, of being <hi>acceſſary</hi> to the draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on us the ſad events we ſpeak of, had need to examine again and again whether the grounds upon which
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:66155:81"/>they have made or incouraged thoſe diviſions, which have been the cauſe of them, be ſuch as will abide the trial before God: and whether they have any ground to think that what they contend for, in caſe they could ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, would ever countervail, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſate the damage which Religion in its reputation, and the Souls of men have already ſuſtained and are like farther to ſuffer, by the courſe they have taken to effect it.</p>
            <p>And when ever they do enter into ſuch conſideration, it will doubtleſs be their wiſdome not to flatter them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with conceit (as I fear ſome do) as if they are not, nor can be <hi>acceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> to the bringing on us theſe ſad effects of our diviſions, but that they are wholly owing and imputable to our Governours, who, as they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps ſuppoſe, have given them juſt occaſion of withdrawing from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in the publick worſhip by making the terms of it ſo difficult and unſatisfactory as they have done.
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:66155:81"/>For tho' that which they ſurmiſe ſhould be ſo far true, <hi>viz.</hi> That the conditions of communion are made more uneaſie unto ſome than they need to be, yet it will not follow but that tho' the Governours in ſome reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect do ill in doing ſo, the people may do very well in ſubmitting to them, tho' leſs pleaſing to themſelves, rather than by cauſing diviſions, by not ſubmitting to them, to draw on ſuch things as may well diſpleaſe them much more than the uneaſie terms of Communion need to do, as long as they are but only <hi>leſs deſirable</hi> and not <hi>abſolutely ſinful</hi> in themſelves, as doubtleſs thoſe in queſtion are not: For if they were, it would be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful that ſo many wiſe, inquiſitive and good men as well of the old Nonconformiſts as others, as ſince the Reformation have ſubmitted to them, ſhould not be ſenſible of it; No not after all that could be ſaid to work ſuch a ſenſe in them by ſuch as have turned every ſtone to do it. And
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:66155:82"/>it is not altogether inconſiderable to remember, that however the caſe is now, yet in the Apoſtles dayes they were ſuch Chriſtians as were <hi>leſs knowing</hi> in the right uſe of their Chriſtian Liberty, that cauſed trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in the Church about things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different in their own nature, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I have noted upon this occaſion, for no worſe end than to ſatisfie the Scrupulous, That al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they ſhould not or could not be perſwaded that our external form of publick worſhip is beſt in it ſelf, yet that to conform to the uſe of it under preſent Circumſtances, is not only lawful, but alſo very <hi>much better</hi> than to be <hi>acceſſary</hi> to all the evil effects and conſequences of our diviſions and cauſeleſs Separations; and that there is upon account of the danger of being ſo, <hi>much more cauſe</hi> to ſcruple <hi>Nonconformity</hi> than Conformity to our form of publick
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:66155:82"/>worſhip. But if all the arguings and reaſonings which have been uſed by many ſhall ſtill fall ſhort of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired effects to cloſe up our unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py breaches, and to heal our diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; the conſequences of them are ſo dreadful, that I could then heartily wiſh, that if the Higher powers think it fit, and rather than the wounds of our Church ſhould be ſtill kept bleed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the exhauſting of her ſtrength and the endangering her very life and being, that a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> were made of ſome ſuch things as can leaſt be born with and beſt ſpar'd, to the publick peace and tranquillity of the Church, if that might procure it; Peace and Edification being the ends unto which all External circumſtances of order are to be accommodated by way of means.</p>
            <p>Thus much I thought good to add, touching the point of Expediency from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s example.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
